<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss  xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" 
      xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" 
      xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" 
      xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" 
      version="2.0">
<channel>
<title>Andrew Mitchell</title>
<link>https://drandrewmitchell.com/research/papers.html</link>
<atom:link href="https://drandrewmitchell.com/research/papers.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
<description>Personal website of Andrew Mitchell</description>
<generator>quarto-1.3.450</generator>
<lastBuildDate>Sun, 20 Aug 2023 00:00:00 GMT</lastBuildDate>
<item>
  <title>A conceptual framework for the practical use of predictive models and Soundscape Indices: Goals, constraings, and applications</title>
  <dc:creator>Andrew Mitchell</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Andrew Mitchell</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Francesco Aletta</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Tin Oberman</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Mercede Erfanian</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Jian Kang</dc:creator>
  <link>https://drandrewmitchell.com/research/papers/2023-08-20_Internoise-framework/InterNoise2023_Mitchell_Predictive_Model_Framework.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<section id="introduction" class="level2" data-number="1">
<h2 data-number="1" class="anchored" data-anchor-id="introduction"><span class="header-section-number">1</span> Introduction</h2>
<p>As the future of urban sound research and practice moves toward a more holistic soundscape focus, the ability to affect change at large scales and in a wide range of projects will require that familiar engineering tools and approaches can be applied to soundscape design. When attempting to apply soundscape in practice in the built environment, it becomes apparent that a predictive model of the users’ perceptual response to the acoustic environment is necessary. Whether to determine the impact of a design change, or to integrate a large scale data at neighbourhood and city levels, a mathematical model of the interacting factors will form a vital component of the implementation of the soundscape approach.</p>
<p>Current methods of assessing soundscapes are generally limited to a post hoc assessment of the existing environment, where users of the space in question are surveyed regarding their experience of the acoustic environment <span class="citation" data-cites="Engel2018Review Zhang2018Effect Ba2019Effect">(Engel et al. 2018; Zhang et al. 2018; Ba and Kang 2019)</span>. While this approach has proved useful in identifying the impacts of an existing environment, designers require the ability to predict how a change or proposed design will impact the soundscape of the space, before its implementation. To this end, a model that is built on measurable or estimate-able quantities of the environment would represent a leap forward in the ability to design soundscapes and to assess their broad impacts on health and wellbeing.</p>
<p>We will begin by outlining the use cases of predictive soundscape models and how they are necessary for certain applications. From the desired use cases, we will then outline a framework within which practical predictive models can be developed.</p>
</section>
<section id="defining-what-a-predictive-soundscape-model-is" class="level2" data-number="2">
<h2 data-number="2" class="anchored" data-anchor-id="defining-what-a-predictive-soundscape-model-is"><span class="header-section-number">2</span> Defining what a predictive soundscape model is</h2>
<p><span class="citation" data-cites="Aletta2016Soundscape">Aletta, Kang, and Axelsson (2016)</span> provide a review of the soundscape descriptors and indicators commonly used in soundscape research and outlines an initial framework for developing predictive soundscape models. In their review, the authors identified eight potential soundscape descriptors, including perceived affective quality <span class="citation" data-cites="Axelsson2010principal">(Axelsson, Nilsson, and Berglund 2010)</span>, restorativeness <span class="citation" data-cites="Payne2013production">(Payne 2013)</span>, etc. Similarly, the authors identified a range of potential indicators used to characterise the acoustic environment, including environmental acoustics indicators such as <img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?L_%7BAeq%7D">, <img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?L_%7BCeq%7D%20%E2%88%92%20L_%7BAeq%7D"> and psychoacoustic indicators such as Loudness (<img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?N_5">) and Sharpness (S).</p>
<p>However, it is noted that several studies show that no single psychoacoustic indicator alone can explain the variation in soundscape responses (as expressed via the descriptors) (e.g. <span class="citation" data-cites="PerssonWaye2002Psycho">(Persson Waye and Öhrström 2002)</span>). The goal of statistical modelling, therefore is to create a more complex and complete representation of the relationship between soundscape indicators and descriptors, beyond what any single indicator could achieve.</p>
<p>Figure&nbsp;1 shows a conceptual view of this relationship. We start with <strong>soundscape indicators</strong>, which characterise the physical and contextual environment to which the listener is exposed. This can be broken down into <strong>sonic features</strong> (e.g.&nbsp;the acoustical features listed above) and <strong>characteristics of the space itself</strong> (e.g.&nbsp;the amount of visible sky, the intended use-case of the space, how crowded the space is, etc.). In order to translate from the physical inputs to an expressed description of the soundscape perception, we introduce the concept of a <strong>perceptual mapping</strong> <span class="citation" data-cites="Lionello2021new">(Lionello 2021)</span>. This mapping represents a simplified idea of how each individual’s brain processes the inputs from the soundscape which they experience, forms a perception, and finally expresses that perception through their description of the soundscape. For our purposes, this perceptual mapping is treated as essentially a black box mapping inputs to outputs. It can be conceived of as a network of weights in which certain characteristics of the sound may have different weights and directions depending on the context, through which all of the inputs are processed, resulting in the soundscape rating. Conceptually, this perceptual mapping – the pathways and weightings through which the inputs are processed before being expressed as a perceptual descriptor – is established prior to an individual’s exposure to the soundscape in question.</p>
<div id="fig-model" class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center anchored">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://drandrewmitchell.com/research/papers/2023-08-20_Internoise-framework/Overall_Model_Concept_Diagram_2022-04-28.png" class="img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption class="figure-caption">Figure&nbsp;1: The conceptual model of soundscape perception, illustrating the perceptual mapping from physical inputs, through personal experience, to soundscape descriptors. The role of the statistical model is to attempt to approximate or reflect this perceptual mappint. Reproduced with permission from <span class="citation" data-cites="Mitchell2022Predictive">Mitchell (2022)</span></figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>It should be made clear that this represents a very simplified view of how a soundscape perception is formed, however it provides a useful conceptual framework for the purposes of understanding and modelling how someone’s perception forms in response to their exposure to a space. One way to consider the function of a statistical model of soundscape perception is as replicating the perceptual mapping between soundscape indicators and descriptors <span class="citation" data-cites="Lionello2021new">(Lionello 2021)</span>. As a person experiences an urban space, they are exposed to an array of physical inputs, these are then processed by the listener through their own personal experience and mapped to their perception of that space. This perception is then expressed through their description of this experience of the soundscape. It is this mapping of physical inputs to perceptual description which the statistical model aims to reflect. The most successful model would then accurately replicate the general perceptual mapping across the population.</p>
</section>
<section id="applications-in-design-and-mapping" class="level2" data-number="3">
<h2 data-number="3" class="anchored" data-anchor-id="applications-in-design-and-mapping"><span class="header-section-number">3</span> Applications in design and mapping</h2>
<p>The soundscape approach faces several challenges in practical applications which are unaddressed by current assessment methods, but which may be solved through the development of a predictive modelling framework. The first of these challenges is predicting how a change in an existing sound environment will be reflected in the soundscape perception. While it is possible in this scenario to measure the existing soundscape perception via questionnaire surveys, if a change is then introduced to the acoustic environment, it is so far impossible to say what the resulting soundscape change would be. This question relates strongly to the idea of soundscape interventions; where a particular noise pollution challenge is addressed by introducing more pleasant sounds (e.g.&nbsp;a water feature), following the soundscape principle of treating sound as a resource <span class="citation" data-cites="Lavia2016Soundscape Moshona2022What">(Lavia et al. 2016; Moshona et al. 2022)</span>. Predicting how much a particular intervention would improve the soundscape (or, indeed whether it would improve at all) is not yet possible with the retrospective methods available.</p>
<p>Several studies have attempted to address this gap by developing machine learning or statistical models of soundscape perception which are focussed on prediction, rather than inference. An array of modelling techniques are used, with linear regression being the most common <span class="citation" data-cites="Lionello2020systematic">(Lionello, Aletta, and Kang 2020)</span>, and also including artificial neural networks (ANN) <span class="citation" data-cites="PuyanaRomero2016Modelling Yu2009Modeling">(Puyana Romero et al. 2016; Yu and Kang 2009)</span> and support vector regression (SVR) <span class="citation" data-cites="Fan2016Automatic Fan2017Emo Giannakopoulos2019Athens">(Fan, Thorogood, and Pasquier 2016, 2017; Giannakopoulos, Orfanidi, and Perantonis 2019)</span>. However, these studies have focussed primarily on using these models to investigate the constructs of soundscape perception, with few efforts to put the models themselves to use. <span class="citation" data-cites="Mitchell2021Investigating">Mitchell et al. (2021)</span> attempted to address this by both developing a predictive model and applying it to an applied scenario where traditional assessment methods were impractical. In a unique application, <span class="citation" data-cites="Ooi2022Probably">Ooi et al. (2022)</span> created a predictive model of soundscape pleasantness which fed an automated and reactive soundscape enhancement system <span class="citation" data-cites="Watcharasupat2022Autonomous">(Watcharasupat et al. 2022)</span>.</p>
<p>Retrospective methods also struggle to capture the dynamics of the soundscape in a space. Whether through the narrative interview method of ISO/TS 12913-2 <span class="citation" data-cites="ISO12913Part2">(ISO/TS 12913-2:2018 2018)</span>, through soundwalks, or through in situ questionnaires <span class="citation" data-cites="Mitchell2020Soundscape">(Mitchell et al. 2020)</span>, only the soundscape during the particular period which the researchers are actively investigating is captured. This makes it very difficult to determine diurnal, seasonal, or yearly patterns of the soundscape. These patterns may be driven by corresponding diurnal, seasonal, or yearly patterns in the acoustic or visual environment, or by variations in how people process and respond to the sound at different times of day/season/year. Currently the only way to investigate any of these patterns is through repeated surveys. Predictive modelling, on the other hand, could allow a trained soundscape model to be paired with longterm monitoring methods to track how a soundscape perception may change in response to changes in the acoustic environment.</p>
<p>Similarly, a move towards modelling methods based on objective and/or measurable factors would facilitate the application of mapping in soundscape. While noise maps have become common in urban noise research and legislation <span class="citation" data-cites="EEA2020Environmental Gasco2020Social">(EEA 2020; Gasco et al. 2020)</span>, they can be difficult to translate into a soundscape approach. The Environmental Noise Directive (END) <span class="citation" data-cites="EuropeanUnion2002Directive">(European Union 2002)</span>, first implemented in 2002, is the main EU instrument to identify noise pollution impacts and track urban noise levels across the EU. Its goals were to determine the population’s exposure to environmental noise, make information on environmental noise available to the public, and prevent and reduce environmental noise and its effects. In general, noise maps are based on modelled traffic flows, from which decibel levels are extrapolated and mapped, although interpolation and mobile measurement methods have also been recently developed <span class="citation" data-cites="Aumond2018Probabilistic">(see Aumond, Jacquesson, and Can 2018)</span>. Alternatively, they can be produced using longterm SLMs or sensor networks. While these methods have significant utility for tracking increases in urban noise levels and are important for determining the health and societal impacts of noise on a large scale, their restricted focus on noise levels alone limits their scope and reduces the potential for identifying more nuanced health and psychological effects of urban sound.</p>
<p>Several studies have attempted to bring soundscape to urban noise mapping. The most notable of these attempts <span class="citation" data-cites="Aumond2018Probabilistic Aletta2015Soundscape Hong2017Exploring Kang2018Impact">(Aumond, Jacquesson, and Can 2018; Aletta and Kang 2015; Hong and Jeon 2017; Kang and Aletta 2018)</span> bring new, more sophisticated methods for mapping urban sound (not just noise levels). For instance, all four present methods which map the relative level of various sound sources, producing maps of the spatial distribution of bird sounds, human voices, water sounds, etc. In <span class="citation" data-cites="Aletta2015Soundscape">Aletta and Kang (2015)</span> and <span class="citation" data-cites="Hong2017Exploring">Hong and Jeon (2017)</span> the mapping relied on soundscape surveys conducted in public spaces, then used interpolation methods and basic relationships to the measured noise levels to generate a map of the perceived soundscape over the entire study space. <span class="citation" data-cites="Kang2018model">Kang et al. (2018)</span>, after starting with survey responses, attempted to create a prediction methods which relied only on the audio recordings made in the space to create visual maps of the predicted soundscape perception (i.e.&nbsp;the perceptual attributes ’pleasant’, ’calm’, ’eventful’, ’annoying’, ’chaotic’, ’monotonous’). According to the authors, the prediction and mapping model would follow three steps: (1) sound sources recognition and profiling, (2) prediction of the soundscape’s perceptual attributes, and (3) implementation of soundscape maps. Unfortunately, from the paper, it appears that the prediction model results were not actually used for the mapping and, again, the survey responses from 21 respondents were interpolated to create the soundscape map. Their results indicated how a predictive model could have been slotted into a mapping use-case, but this was limited by (1) the relatively poor predictive performance for several of the attributes, (2) the inability to automatically recognise sound sources, and (3) a very limited dataset in terms of sample size and variety of locations.</p>
<p>While the connection is not made to perception, <span class="citation" data-cites="Aumond2018Probabilistic">Aumond, Jacquesson, and Can (2018)</span> focussed on creating sound maps which can reflect the pattern of sound source emergences over time within a city. By stochastically activating varying sound sources across their map, they could map the percentage of time when a sound source emerges from the overall complex sound environment. If a predictive soundscape model which incorporates sound source information can be developed, then the same procedure which led to their sound source emergence maps could also feed the soundscape model, resulting in a map of predicted perception over time.</p>
<p>Urban scale noise mapping and its implementation at the international level has been crucial in highlighting the health impacts of urban noise and in providing evidence for the negative cost of excess noise. Traffic flow models of noise, large community noise surveys, and policy requirements to track noise levels have all been necessary to reveal these impacts. By creating predictive soundscape models, combined with new tools and sensing capabilities from smart city efforts, we can bring soundscape into these same realms. Without this, these large-scale impact studies will be limited to valuing the negative cost of urban noise, missing the potential value of positive soundscapes. By bringing perception-based practice to the same scale and type of evidence, we can expand urban sound research to consider a holistic view of urban spaces and their impacts.</p>
<p>The broader use-case and need for such soundscape models and maps was recently highlighted by <span class="citation" data-cites="Jiang2022Ten">Jiang et al. (2022)</span>, which opens the discussion for how the value and impact of soundscapes should be measured and what tools are needed to enable the valuation of policy interventions for soundscapes. In response to Question 5, “What soundscape metrics and data will be needed?”, the authors make clear the necessity of predictive soundscape models: “Quantitative soundscape metrics that link subjective perceptions to objective acoustic and contextual factors will be needed, to enable monetisation while at the same time account for the perception-based nature of soundscape.” In addition, the authors make a strong case for the need for soundscape indices: “Despite the varied requirements for soundscape metrics and data between and even within valuation methods, a standardised metric or set of metrics, such as dB in noise valuation [. . . ] will allow comparison and integration of different studies and building compatible evidence bases.”</p>
</section>
<section id="the-predictive-soundscape-model-framework" class="level2" data-number="4">
<h2 data-number="4" class="anchored" data-anchor-id="the-predictive-soundscape-model-framework"><span class="header-section-number">4</span> The Predictive Soundscape Model Framework</h2>
<p>Several forms and iterations of predictive models have been developed <span class="citation" data-cites="Lionello2020systematic">(Lionello, Aletta, and Kang 2020)</span> and more recently they have been put to use in real-world use cases <span class="citation" data-cites="Mitchell2021Investigating Watcharasupat2022Autonomous">(Mitchell et al. 2021; Watcharasupat et al. 2022)</span>. To improve on these models and make them into a useful engineering tool, we should establish a framework of overarching goals for models to achieve and the resulting development constraints. In general, the goals we define are related to how we might wish for models to be used and deployed, while the constraints are practical limitations which may make the performance of a given model less than ideal, but are necessary to achieve the deployment goals.</p>
<section id="goals" class="level3" data-number="4.1">
<h3 data-number="4.1" class="anchored" data-anchor-id="goals"><span class="header-section-number">4.1</span> Goals</h3>
<p>Before defining what form a general practical predictive model should take, we first need to make clear what the goals of such a model are, as derived from the preceding discussion laying out why predictive models are needed in soundscape.</p>
<p><strong>Accuracy</strong> – First, that it to a reasonable extent is successful in predicting the collective perception <span class="citation" data-cites="Mitchell2022How">(see Mitchell, Aletta, and Kang 2022)</span> of a soundscape. It should succeed at both indicating the central tendency of the soundscape perception, but importantly it should also inform the likely spread of perception among the population. The outcome of the predictive model should not be focussed on predicting an individual assessment; the goal is not the predict the perception of any specific individual, but to reflect the public’s perception of a public space. In other words, ideally the model will result in an accurate distribution of soundscape perceptions for the target population.</p>
<p><strong>Automation</strong> – Second, that it can be implemented automatically. Once an initial setup is performed, such as identifying what location the measurements are conducted in, the model should be capable of moving from recorded information to predicted soundscape distribution without human intervention. We need soundscape assessments to be able to be performed instrumentally. This enables it to be applied to unmanned uses, such as smart city sensors and soundscape mapping. It is impractical to conduct soundscape surveys or soundwalks in every location we wish to map and certainly not when we wish to see how these locations change over longer periods of time. A predictive model should allow us to survey these soundscapes remotely in order to extend soundscape to city-scale assessments.</p>
<p><strong>Comparisons</strong> – Third, the model should enable us to test, score, and compare proposed interventions. In a design context, it is crucial that various strategies and interventions can be tested and that the influencing factors can be identified. The model should assist the user in highlighting what factor is limiting the success of a soundscape, spark ideas for how to address it, and allow these ideas to be tested. Several other useful features of predictive soundscape models arise out of these goals and will be discussed later, but these form the core goals of the framework.</p>
</section>
<section id="constraints" class="level3" data-number="4.2">
<h3 data-number="4.2" class="anchored" data-anchor-id="constraints"><span class="header-section-number">4.2</span> Constraints</h3>
<p>If we accept that predictive models are necessary to advance a more holistic approach to urban sound in smart cities, we must then define the constraints of such a model. The goal here is to define a framework for what is needed from a future model intended to be used in a smart city sensors, soundscape mapping, or urban design context.</p>
<p><strong>Inputs</strong> – The first constraint is that the model must be based on measurable factors. By this, we mean that the data which eventually feeds into the predictive model should be collected via sensor measurements of one sort or another; this could be acoustic sound level measurements or recordings, environmental measurements, video recordings, or GIS measurements, etc. What it certainly cannot include is perceptual data. This is strictly a practical constraint – for a predictive model designed to be used in practice, there is no justification to include other perceptual factors, such as perceived greenness, derived from surveys but not whichever factor you desire to predict. If the goal is to predict soundscape pleasantness and it is necessary to survey people about the visual pleasantness, why not just also survey them about the soundscape pleasantness directly? Certainly this mix of perceptual data is useful in research and can elucidate the relationship between the sonic and visual environments, but it is not useful in a practical predictive context. Any results which arise from research combining this sort of perceptual information must eventually be translated into a component which can itself be measured or modelled.</p>
<p><strong>Calculation</strong> – The second constraint is that any analysis of the measured data can be done automatically, without human intervention. If the eventual goal is to deploy the model on continuously-running, unmanned sensor nodes or to enable practical large-scale measurements, the predictive model should be capable of operating with minimal human input. This means, for instance that if the model includes information about the sound source, this identification of the source should be possible to do automatically (i.e.&nbsp;through environmental sound recognition).</p>
<p>A potential constraint for some applications is related to computation time. Since one proposed application of a predictive soundscape model is to embed the model on a WASN node, the model would then need to be able to run on relatively low-power hardware such as a Raspberry Pi with a reasonable latency. This would especially present an issue for those models which rely on the combination of several psychoacoustic features <span class="citation" data-cites="Mitchell2021Investigating Orga2021Multilevel">(such as Mitchell et al. 2021; Orga et al. 2021)</span>, since these features are computationally intensive to calculate and several of them may need to be computed for each time step of the model. Although this is a real practical concern that should be addressed in the future, for the sake of this initial definition of a general predictive model used across many applications, we have not considered this a strict constraint.</p>
<p><strong>Generalisability</strong> – The third constraint is for the model to be generalisable to new locations. Ideally, it will be generalisable to new and (to it) unfamiliar soundscape types, but the minimum requirement should be that it can be applied to new locations which are otherwise similar to those in the training data. This means that any factors which are used to characterise the context provided by the location should be distinguished from a simple label of the location and should instead be derived from measurements of the location. In practice this could be geographical or architectural characteristics of the space, a proposed use-case of the space, or consistent visual characteristics of the space such as the proportion of pavement to green elements. This is in contrast to the model created in <span class="citation" data-cites="Mitchell2021Investigating">Mitchell et al. (2021)</span> which was constrained to be used only on those locations included in the training data since it made use of a location label.</p>
<p>For this third point, some aspects of the first and second constraints can be relaxed. Since this would only need to be defined once for a location, definitions such as the use case of the space could be defined by the person using the model. What is necessary is that the model and its component location-context factors can be set up ahead of time by the user, then the recording-level effects are able to be calculated automatically. In a multi-level modelling (MLM) context (such as that used in <span class="citation" data-cites="Mitchell2021Investigating">(Mitchell et al. 2021)</span>, this essentially amounts to choosing the appropriate location-level coefficients ahead of time then automatically calculating the features which are fed into those coefficients (per constraint 1 &amp; 2).</p>
<p><strong>Robustness</strong> – Finally, the model should be robust to missing components. If the original or full construction of the model depends on demographic information of the population using the space, in cases where this information is not available, it should be possible to omit it and still obtain a reasonable result. Here we may define potential ‘must-have’ and ‘optional’ factors. Given the amount of variance explained by the various factors which have been considered in previous predictive models, in-depth acoustic information is a must-have, while demographic and personal factors are an optional factor where the trade-off of losing 3% of the explained variance in eventfulness <span class="citation" data-cites="Erfanian2021Psychological">(Erfanian et al. 2021)</span> is accepted as reasonable. Based on the results of <span class="citation" data-cites="Mitchell2021Investigating">Mitchell et al. (2021)</span>, it would appear that location-context is crucial for modelling the pleasantness, but not for modelling the eventfulness. In order to determine the must-have factors for characterising the location-context, more work will need to be done to determine the appropriate input factors and their relative importance.</p>
</section>
</section>
<section id="making-use-of-the-predictions-in-design" class="level2" data-number="5">
<h2 data-number="5" class="anchored" data-anchor-id="making-use-of-the-predictions-in-design"><span class="header-section-number">5</span> Making use of the predictions in design</h2>
<p>There are various potential methods for integrating the predictive soundscape approach into a design and intervention setting. Not all spaces can or should have the same soundscape and soundscapes should be treated as dynamic, not static; identifying and creating an appropriate soundscape for the particular use case of a space is crucial to guiding its design. Proper forwardlooking design of a soundscape would involve defining the desired collective perception in the space. In the probabilistic soundscape approach from <span class="citation" data-cites="Mitchell2022How">Mitchell, Aletta, and Kang (2022)</span>, this can be achieved by drawing the desired shape in the circumplex and testing interventions which will bring the existing soundscape closer to the desired perception. A soundscape may need to be perceived as vibrant during the day and calm for some portion of the evening, meaning the desired shape should primarily sit within the vibrant quadrant but have some overlap into calm. This also enables designers to recognise the limitations of their environment and acknowledge that it is not always possible to transform a highly chaotic soundscape into a calm one. In these cases, instead the focus should be placed on shifting the perception to some degree in a positive direction.</p>
<div id="fig-cain" class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center anchored">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://drandrewmitchell.com/research/papers/2023-08-20_Internoise-framework/CainCircumplexTarget.png" class="img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption class="figure-caption">Figure&nbsp;2: Adapted from <span class="citation" data-cites="Cain2013development">Cain, Jennings, and Poxon (2013)</span>. Using the soundscape circumplex shape for target-setting for soundscape design. Reproduced with permission from <span class="citation" data-cites="Mitchell2022Predictive">Mitchell (2022)</span>.</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>The most sophisticated method of setting design goals is therefore to identify the desired shape which represents the variety of desired outcomes, and focus on designs and interventions which are most successful in matching the predicted outcome with that goal. This strategy of defining the optimal soundscape as an area or a shape within the 2-dimensional circumplex was previously illustrated by <span class="citation" data-cites="Cain2013development">Cain, Jennings, and Poxon (2013)</span>. In Figure&nbsp;2, we have adapted Cain’s Figure 6 to show how the shape of a target soundscape can be set and the shape of the existing soundscape compared to it. The work of a designer is then trialling intervention options which move the design soundscape closer to the target soundscape.</p>
</section>
<section id="towards-soundscape-indices" class="level2" data-number="6">
<h2 data-number="6" class="anchored" data-anchor-id="towards-soundscape-indices"><span class="header-section-number">6</span> Towards Soundscape Indices</h2>
<p>Although the types of visualisations developed in <span class="citation" data-cites="Mitchell2022How">(Mitchell, Aletta, and Kang 2022)</span> and <span class="citation" data-cites="Cain2013development">(Cain, Jennings, and Poxon 2013)</span> are a powerful tool for viewing, analysing, and discussing the multi-dimensional aspects of soundscape perception, there are certainly cases where simpler metrics are needed to aid discussion and to set design goals. Within the practicalities of built environment projects, the consequences and successes of a design often need to be quantifiable within a single index. Whether to demonstrate performance indicators to a client or to set and meet consistent policy requirements, numerical ratings and/or rankings are necessary. This therefore necessitates the creation of consistent and validated indices which indicate the degree to which a proposal achieves a set design goal.</p>
<p>The challenge for creating a single number index lies in properly combining the two-plus dimensions of soundscape perception with the needs of a specific project into a single index. The obvious option would be to ignore the multi-dimensionality and only score soundscape designs on the basis of their pleasantness score (as done in <span class="citation" data-cites="Ooi2022Probably">(Ooi et al. 2022)</span>). However, this seems to ignore both the significant importance of the eventfulness dimension in shaping the character of a soundscape and the role of appropriateness in determining the ’optimal soundscape’ for a space. Ideally, a soundscape index (or set of soundscape indices) would succeed at capturing all these aspects into a single scoring metric.</p>
</section>
<section id="conclusion" class="level2" data-number="7">
<h2 data-number="7" class="anchored" data-anchor-id="conclusion"><span class="header-section-number">7</span> Conclusion</h2>
<p>The existing methods for soundscape assessment and measurement, such as those given in the ISO 12913 series, have been focussed primarily on determining the status quo of an environment. That is, they are able to determine how the space is currently perceived, but offer little insight into hypothetical environments. As such, they are less relevant for design purposes, where a key goal is to determine how a space will be perceived, not just how an existing space is perceived. The methods for assessment outlined in <span class="citation" data-cites="ISO12913Part2">ISO/TS 12913-2:2018 (2018)</span> and for analysis given in <span class="citation" data-cites="ISO12913Part3">ISO/TS 12913-3:2019 (2019)</span> are inherently limited to post hoc assessments of an existing space. Since they are focussed on surveying people on their experience of the environment, it stands that the space must already exist for people to be able to experience. Toward this, and following from the combination of perceptual and objective data collection encouraged in <span class="citation" data-cites="ISO12913Part2">ISO/TS 12913-2:2018 (2018)</span>, the natural push from the design perspective is towards ’predictive modelling’.</p>
</section>
<section id="references" class="level2 unnumbered">




</section>

<div id="quarto-appendix" class="default"><section class="quarto-appendix-contents"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">References</h2><div id="refs" class="references csl-bib-body hanging-indent">
<div id="ref-Aletta2015Soundscape" class="csl-entry">
Aletta, Francesco, and Jian Kang. 2015. <span>“<span class="nocase">Soundscape approach integrating noise mapping techniques: a case study in Brighton, UK</span>.”</span> <em>Noise Mapping</em> 2 (1): 1–12. <a href="https://doi.org/10.1515/noise-2015-0001">https://doi.org/10.1515/noise-2015-0001</a>.
</div>
<div id="ref-Aletta2016Soundscape" class="csl-entry">
Aletta, Francesco, Jian Kang, and Östen Axelsson. 2016. <span>“<span class="nocase">Soundscape descriptors and a conceptual framework for developing predictive soundscape models</span>.”</span> <em>Landscape and Urban Planning</em> 149 (July): 65–74. <a href="https://doi.org/10.1016/j.landurbplan.2016.02.001">https://doi.org/10.1016/j.landurbplan.2016.02.001</a>.
</div>
<div id="ref-Aumond2018Probabilistic" class="csl-entry">
Aumond, Pierre, Léo Jacquesson, and Arnaud Can. 2018. <span>“Probabilistic Modeling Framework for Multisource Sound Mapping.”</span> <em>Applied Acoustics</em> 139 (October): 34–43. <a href="https://doi.org/10.1016/j.apacoust.2018.04.017">https://doi.org/10.1016/j.apacoust.2018.04.017</a>.
</div>
<div id="ref-Axelsson2010principal" class="csl-entry">
Axelsson, Östen, Mats E. Nilsson, and Birgitta Berglund. 2010. <span>“<span class="nocase">A principal components model of soundscape perception</span>.”</span> <em>The Journal of the Acoustical Society of America</em> 128 (5): 2836–46. <a href="https://doi.org/10.1121/1.3493436">https://doi.org/10.1121/1.3493436</a>.
</div>
<div id="ref-Ba2019Effect" class="csl-entry">
Ba, Meihui, and Jian Kang. 2019. <span>“<span class="nocase">Effect of a fragrant tree on the perception of traffic noise</span>.”</span> <em>Building and Environment</em>. <a href="https://doi.org/10.1016/j.buildenv.2019.04.022">https://doi.org/10.1016/j.buildenv.2019.04.022</a>.
</div>
<div id="ref-Cain2013development" class="csl-entry">
Cain, Rebecca, Paul Jennings, and John Poxon. 2013. <span>“The Development and Application of the Emotional Dimensions of a Soundscape.”</span> <em>Applied Acoustics</em> 74 (2): 232–39. <a href="https://doi.org/10.1016/j.apacoust.2011.11.006">https://doi.org/10.1016/j.apacoust.2011.11.006</a>.
</div>
<div id="ref-EEA2020Environmental" class="csl-entry">
EEA. 2020. <span>“<span class="nocase">Environmental noise in <span>Europe</span>, 2020.</span>”</span> Publications Office of the European Union. <a href="https://doi.org/10.2800/686249">https://doi.org/10.2800/686249</a>.
</div>
<div id="ref-Engel2018Review" class="csl-entry">
Engel, Margret Sibylle, André Fiebig, Carmella Pfaffenbach, and Janina Fels. 2018. <span>“<span class="nocase">A <span>Review</span> of <span>Socio</span>-acoustic <span>Surveys</span> for <span>Soundscape</span> <span>Studies</span></span>.”</span> <em>Current Pollution Reports</em> 4 (3): 220–39. <a href="https://doi.org/10.1007/s40726-018-0094-8">https://doi.org/10.1007/s40726-018-0094-8</a>.
</div>
<div id="ref-Erfanian2021Psychological" class="csl-entry">
Erfanian, Mercede, Andrew Mitchell, Francesco Aletta, and Jian Kang. 2021. <span>“Psychological Well-Being and Demographic Factors Can Mediate Soundscape Pleasantness and Eventfulness: A Large Sample Study.”</span> <em>Journal of Environmental Psychology</em> 77 (October): 101660. <a href="https://doi.org/10.1016/j.jenvp.2021.101660">https://doi.org/10.1016/j.jenvp.2021.101660</a>.
</div>
<div id="ref-EuropeanUnion2002Directive" class="csl-entry">
European Union. 2002. <em><span class="nocase">Directive 2002/49/EC of the European Parliament and of the Council of 25 June 2002 relating to the assessment and management of environmental noise</span></em>.
</div>
<div id="ref-Fan2016Automatic" class="csl-entry">
Fan, Jianyu, Miles Thorogood, and Philippe Pasquier. 2016. <span>“<span>Automatic Soundscape Affect Recognition Using A Dimensional Approach</span>.”</span> <em>AES: Journal of the Audio Engineering Society</em> 64 (9): 646–53. <a href="https://doi.org/10.17743/jaes.2016.0044">https://doi.org/10.17743/jaes.2016.0044</a>.
</div>
<div id="ref-Fan2017Emo" class="csl-entry">
———. 2017. <span>“Emo-Soundscapes: A Dataset for Soundscape Emotion Recognition.”</span> In <em>2017 Seventh International Conference on Affective Computing and Intelligent Interaction (ACII)</em>, 196–201. <a href="https://doi.org/10.1109/ACII.2017.8273600">https://doi.org/10.1109/ACII.2017.8273600</a>.
</div>
<div id="ref-Gasco2020Social" class="csl-entry">
Gasco, Luis, Rossano Schifanella, Luca Maria Aiello, Daniele Quercia, Cesar Asensio, and Guillermo de Arcas. 2020. <span>“<span class="nocase">Social Media and Open Data to Quantify the Effects of Noise on Health</span>.”</span> <em>Frontiers in Sustainable Cities</em> 2 (September): 41. <a href="https://doi.org/10.3389/frsc.2020.00041">https://doi.org/10.3389/frsc.2020.00041</a>.
</div>
<div id="ref-Giannakopoulos2019Athens" class="csl-entry">
Giannakopoulos, Theodoros, Margarita Orfanidi, and Stavros Perantonis. 2019. <span>“<span class="nocase">Athens Urban Soundscape (ATHUS): A Dataset for Urban Soundscape Quality Recognition</span>.”</span> In <em>International Conference on Multimedia Modeling</em>, 11295:338–48. Springer International Publishing. <a href="https://doi.org/10.1007/978-3-319-14442-9">https://doi.org/10.1007/978-3-319-14442-9</a>.
</div>
<div id="ref-Hong2017Exploring" class="csl-entry">
Hong, Joo Young, and Jin Yong Jeon. 2017. <span>“Exploring Spatial Relationships Among Soundscape Variables in Urban Areas: A Spatial Statistical Modelling Approach.”</span> <em>Landscape and Urban Planning</em> 157 (January): 352–64. <a href="https://doi.org/10.1016/j.landurbplan.2016.08.006">https://doi.org/10.1016/j.landurbplan.2016.08.006</a>.
</div>
<div id="ref-ISO12913Part2" class="csl-entry">
ISO/TS 12913-2:2018. 2018. <span>“<span>Acoustics</span> – <span>Soundscape</span> – <span>Part</span> 2: <span>Data</span> Collection and Reporting Requirements.”</span>
</div>
<div id="ref-ISO12913Part3" class="csl-entry">
ISO/TS 12913-3:2019. 2019. <span>“<span>Acoustics</span> – <span>Soundscape</span> – <span>Part</span> 3: <span>Data</span> Analysis.”</span>
</div>
<div id="ref-Jiang2022Ten" class="csl-entry">
Jiang, Like, Aibgail Bristow, Jian Kang, Francesco Aletta, Rhian Thomas, Hilary Notley, Adam Thomas, and John Nellthorp. 2022. <span>“Ten Questions Concerning Soundscape Valuation.”</span> <em>Building and Environments</em>, May, 109231. <a href="https://doi.org/10.1016/j.buildenv.2022.109231">https://doi.org/10.1016/j.buildenv.2022.109231</a>.
</div>
<div id="ref-Kang2018Impact" class="csl-entry">
Kang, Jian, and Francesco Aletta. 2018. <span>“<span class="nocase">The Impact and Outreach of Soundscape Research</span>.”</span> <em>Environments</em> 5 (5): 58. <a href="https://doi.org/10.3390/environments5050058">https://doi.org/10.3390/environments5050058</a>.
</div>
<div id="ref-Kang2018model" class="csl-entry">
Kang, Jian, Francesco Aletta, Efstathios Margaritis, and Ming Yang. 2018. <span>“A Model for Implementing Soundscape Maps in Smart Cities.”</span> <em>Noise Mapping</em> 5 (1): 46–59. <a href="https://doi.org/10.1515/noise-2018-0004">https://doi.org/10.1515/noise-2018-0004</a>.
</div>
<div id="ref-Lavia2016Soundscape" class="csl-entry">
Lavia, Lisa, Max Dixon, Harry J. Witchel, and Mike Goldsmith. 2016. <span>“Soundscape and the <span>B</span>uilt <span>E</span>nvironment.”</span> In, edited by Jian Kang and Brigitte Schulte-Fortkamp, 243–302. Boca Raton, FL: CRC Press.
</div>
<div id="ref-Lionello2021new" class="csl-entry">
Lionello, Matteo. 2021. <span>“A New Methodology for Modelling Urban Soundscapes: <span>A</span> Psychometric Revisitation of the Current Standard and a <span>Bayesian</span> Approach for Individual Response Prediction.”</span> Master’s thesis, Unpublished. <a href="https://doi.org/10.13140/RG.2.2.30107.80160">https://doi.org/10.13140/RG.2.2.30107.80160</a>.
</div>
<div id="ref-Lionello2020systematic" class="csl-entry">
Lionello, Matteo, Francesco Aletta, and Jian Kang. 2020. <span>“<span class="nocase">A systematic review of prediction models for the experience of urban soundscapes</span>.”</span> <em>Applied Acoustics</em> 170 (June). <a href="https://doi.org/10.1016/j.apacoust.2020.107479">https://doi.org/10.1016/j.apacoust.2020.107479</a>.
</div>
<div id="ref-Mitchell2022Predictive" class="csl-entry">
Mitchell, Andrew. 2022. <span>“Predictive <span>M</span>odelling of <span>C</span>omplex <span>U</span>rban <span>S</span>oundscapes: <span>E</span>nabling an Engineering Approach to Soundscape Design.”</span> PhD Thesis, University College London. <a href="https://doi.org/10.13140/RG.2.2.15590.50245">https://doi.org/10.13140/RG.2.2.15590.50245</a>.
</div>
<div id="ref-Mitchell2022How" class="csl-entry">
Mitchell, Andrew, Francesco Aletta, and Jian Kang. 2022. <span>“How to Analyse and Represent Quantitative Soundscape Data.”</span> <em>JASA Express Letters</em> 2 (3): 037201. <a href="https://doi.org/10.1121/10.0009794">https://doi.org/10.1121/10.0009794</a>.
</div>
<div id="ref-Mitchell2020Soundscape" class="csl-entry">
Mitchell, Andrew, Tin Oberman, Francesco Aletta, Mercede Erfanian, Magdalena Kachlicka, Matteo Lionello, and Jian Kang. 2020. <span>“<span class="nocase">The Soundscape Indices (SSID) Protocol: A Method for Urban Soundscape Surveys–Questionnaires with Acoustical and Contextual Information</span>.”</span> <em>Applied Sciences</em> 10 (7): 2397. <a href="https://doi.org/10.3390/app10072397">https://doi.org/10.3390/app10072397</a>.
</div>
<div id="ref-Mitchell2021Investigating" class="csl-entry">
Mitchell, Andrew, Tin Oberman, Francesco Aletta, Magdalena Kachlicka, Matteo Lionello, Mercede Erfanian, and Jian Kang. 2021. <span>“Investigating Urban Soundscapes of the <span>COVID</span>-19 Lockdown: <span>A</span> Predictive Soundscape Modeling Approach.”</span> <em>The Journal of the Acoustical Society of America</em> 150 (6): 4474–88. <a href="https://doi.org/10.1121/10.0008928">https://doi.org/10.1121/10.0008928</a>.
</div>
<div id="ref-Moshona2022What" class="csl-entry">
Moshona, Cleopatra Christina, Francesco Aletta, Helen Henze, Xiaochao Chen, Andrew Mitchell, Tin Oberman, Huan Tong, André Fiebig, Jian Kang, and Brigitte Schulte-Fortkamp. 2022. <span>“What Is a Soundscape Intervention? Exploring Definitions and Identifi-Cation Criteria and a Platform to Gather Real-World Examples.”</span> In <em>51st International Congress and Exposition on Noise Control Engineering (INTER-NOISE 2022)</em>. <a href="https://www.researchgate.net/profile/Francesco-Aletta/publication/362906252_What_is_a_soundscape_intervention_Exploring_definitions_and_identification_criteria_and_a_platform_to_gather_real-world_examples/links/630664e561e4553b95364712/What-is-a-soundscape-intervention-Exploring-definitions-and-identification-criteria-and-a-platform-to-gather-real-world-examples.pdf">https://www.researchgate.net/profile/Francesco-Aletta/publication/362906252_What_is_a_soundscape_intervention_Exploring_definitions_and_identification_criteria_and_a_platform_to_gather_real-world_examples/links/630664e561e4553b95364712/What-is-a-soundscape-intervention-Exploring-definitions-and-identification-criteria-and-a-platform-to-gather-real-world-examples.pdf</a>.
</div>
<div id="ref-Ooi2022Probably" class="csl-entry">
Ooi, Kenneth, Karn N. Watcharasupat, Bhan Lam, Zhen-Ting Ong, and Woon-Seng Gan. 2022. <span>“Probably Pleasant? A Neural-Probabilistic Approach to Automatic Masker Selection for Urban Soundscape Augmentation.”</span> In <em><span>ICASSP</span> 2022 - 2022 <span>IEEE</span> International Conference on Acoustics, Speech and Signal Processing (<span>ICASSP</span>)</em>. <span>IEEE</span>. <a href="https://doi.org/10.1109/icassp43922.2022.9746897">https://doi.org/10.1109/icassp43922.2022.9746897</a>.
</div>
<div id="ref-Orga2021Multilevel" class="csl-entry">
Orga, Ferran, Andrew Mitchell, Marc Freixes, Francesco Aletta, Rosa Ma Alsina-Pagès, and Maria Foraster. 2021. <span>“<span class="nocase">Multilevel Annoyance Modelling of Short Environmental Sound Recordings</span>.”</span> <em>Sustainability</em> 13 (11): 5779. <a href="https://doi.org/10.3390/su13115779">https://doi.org/10.3390/su13115779</a>.
</div>
<div id="ref-Payne2013production" class="csl-entry">
Payne, Sarah R. 2013. <span>“The Production of a <span>P</span>erceived <span>R</span>estorativeness <span>S</span>oundscape <span>S</span>cale.”</span> <em>Applied Acoustics</em> 74 (2): 255–63. <a href="https://doi.org/10.1016/j.apacoust.2011.11.005">https://doi.org/10.1016/j.apacoust.2011.11.005</a>.
</div>
<div id="ref-PerssonWaye2002Psycho" class="csl-entry">
Persson Waye, K., and E. Öhrström. 2002. <span>“<span>P</span>sycho-Acoustic Characters of Relevance for Annoyance of Wind Turbine Noise.”</span> <em>Journal of Sound and Vibration</em> 250 (1): 65–73. <a href="https://doi.org/10.1006/jsvi.2001.3905">https://doi.org/10.1006/jsvi.2001.3905</a>.
</div>
<div id="ref-PuyanaRomero2016Modelling" class="csl-entry">
Puyana Romero, Virginia, Luigi Maffei, Giovanni Brambilla, and Giuseppe Ciaburro. 2016. <span>“Modelling the Soundscape Quality of Urban Waterfronts by Artificial Neural Networks.”</span> <em>Applied Acoustics</em> 111 (October): 121–28. <a href="https://doi.org/10.1016/j.apacoust.2016.04.019">https://doi.org/10.1016/j.apacoust.2016.04.019</a>.
</div>
<div id="ref-Watcharasupat2022Autonomous" class="csl-entry">
Watcharasupat, Karn N., Kenneth Ooi, Bhan Lam, Trevor Wong, Zhen-Ting Ong, and Woon-Seng Gan. 2022. <span>“Autonomous in-Situ Soundscape Augmentation via Joint Selection of Masker and Gain.”</span> <em><span>IEEE</span> Signal Processing Letters</em> 29: 1749–53. <a href="https://doi.org/10.1109/lsp.2022.3194419">https://doi.org/10.1109/lsp.2022.3194419</a>.
</div>
<div id="ref-Yu2009Modeling" class="csl-entry">
Yu, Lei, and Jian Kang. 2009. <span>“Modeling Subjective Evaluation of Soundscape Quality in Urban Open Spaces: An Artificial Neural Network Approach.”</span> <em>The Journal of the Acoustical Society of America</em> 126 (3): 1163–74. <a href="https://doi.org/10.1121/1.3183377">https://doi.org/10.1121/1.3183377</a>.
</div>
<div id="ref-Zhang2018Effect" class="csl-entry">
Zhang, Xu, Meihui Ba, Jian Kang, and Qi Meng. 2018. <span>“<span class="nocase">Effect of soundscape dimensions on acoustic comfort in urban open public spaces</span>.”</span> <em>Applied Acoustics</em> 133 (April): 73–81. <a href="https://doi.org/10.1016/j.apacoust.2017.11.024">https://doi.org/10.1016/j.apacoust.2017.11.024</a>.
</div>
</div></section><section class="quarto-appendix-contents"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">Reuse</h2><div id="quarto-reuse" class="quarto-appendix-contents"><div><a rel="license" href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</a></div></div></section><section class="quarto-appendix-contents"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">Citation</h2><div><div class="quarto-appendix-secondary-label">BibTeX citation:</div><pre class="sourceCode code-with-copy quarto-appendix-bibtex"><code class="sourceCode bibtex">@inproceedings{mitchell2023,
  author = {Mitchell, Andrew and Aletta, Francesco and Oberman, Tin and
    Erfanian, Mercede and Kang, Jian},
  title = {A Conceptual Framework for the Practical Use of Predictive
    Models and {Soundscape} {Indices:} {Goals,} Constraings, and
    Applications},
  booktitle = {INTER-NOISE 2023 Conference},
  date = {2023-08-20},
  url = {https://drandrewmitchell.com//research/papers/2023-08-20_Internoise-framework/InterNoise2023_Mitchell_Predictive_Model_Framework.html},
  langid = {en},
  abstract = {With the recent standardization of soundscape, there has
    been increased interest in bringing the soundscape approach into an
    engineering context. While traditional assessment methods, such as
    those given in the ISO 12913 series, provide information on the
    current status quo of an environment, they offer limited insight
    into hypothetical environments and are therefore less relevant for
    design purposes. This conference paper presents a conceptual
    framework for the practical use of predictive soundscape models and
    indices. The framework outlines the goals, constraints, and
    potential applications of these models and highlights the need for
    further research in this area to better understand the dynamics of
    soundscape perception and to put predictive models to practical use.
    Predictive soundscape models can be integrated with soundscape
    indices - such as those being developed by the Soundscape Indices
    (SSID) project - for assessment purposes, providing a comprehensive
    approach to evaluating and designing sound environments. The use of
    predictive models is necessary to address the challenges faced in
    practical applications of the soundscape approach and to fill the
    gap between traditional assessment methods and the design of sound
    environments.}
}
</code></pre><div class="quarto-appendix-secondary-label">For attribution, please cite this work as:</div><div id="ref-mitchell2023" class="csl-entry quarto-appendix-citeas">
Mitchell, Andrew, Francesco Aletta, Tin Oberman, Mercede Erfanian, and
Jian Kang. 2023. <span>“A Conceptual Framework for the Practical Use of
Predictive Models and Soundscape Indices: Goals, Constraings, and
Applications .”</span> In <em>INTER-NOISE 2023 Conference</em>. <a href="https://drandrewmitchell.com//research/papers/2023-08-20_Internoise-framework/InterNoise2023_Mitchell_Predictive_Model_Framework.html">https://drandrewmitchell.com//research/papers/2023-08-20_Internoise-framework/InterNoise2023_Mitchell_Predictive_Model_Framework.html</a>.
</div></div></section></div> ]]></description>
  <category>conference-papers</category>
  <guid>https://drandrewmitchell.com/research/papers/2023-08-20_Internoise-framework/InterNoise2023_Mitchell_Predictive_Model_Framework.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Sun, 20 Aug 2023 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
<item>
  <title>How to analyse and represent quantitative soundscape data</title>
  <dc:creator>Andrew Mitchell</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Andrew Mitchell</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Francesco Aletta</dc:creator>
  <dc:creator>Jian Kang</dc:creator>
  <link>https://drandrewmitchell.com/research/papers/how-to-analyse-jasa/index.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<section id="sec-introduction" class="level1" data-number="1">
<h1 data-number="1"><span class="header-section-number">1</span> Introduction</h1>
<p>Methods for collecting data on how people experience acoustic environments have been at the forefront of the debate in soundscape studies for the past 20 years. While the soundscape research field as we understand it today dates back to the late 1960s with the pioneering work of authors like M. Southworth <span class="citation" data-cites="Southworth1969sonic">(Southworth 1969)</span>, R.M. Schafer <span class="citation" data-cites="SoundscapeOursonicSchafer">(Schafer 1977)</span>, and H. Westerkamp <span class="citation" data-cites="westerkamp2002linking">(Westerkamp 2002)</span>, the theme of data collection methods for soundscape assessment emerged more prominently only recently <span class="citation" data-cites="kang2016ten">(Kang et al. 2016)</span>. There is a general consensus in the research community that standardised tools to gather and report individual responses on the perception of urban acoustic environments are indeed desirable, to provide comparable datasets and soundscape characterisations across different locations, times, and samples of people, as well as allowing for replicability studies, and offering inputs for modelling algorithms in soundscape prediction and design tasks. These were among the main drivers for the establishment of a Working Group at the International Organization for Standardization (ISO) back in 2008, which was named “Perceptual assessment of soundscape quality” (ISO/TC 43/SC 1/WG 54) that has so far published three documents within the ISO 12913 series on soundscape. Part 1 (ISO 12913-1:2014) is a full standard and provides a general framework and definitions of soundscape concepts <span class="citation" data-cites="ISO12913_1">(ISO 2014)</span>, while Part 2 (ISO/TS 12913-2:2018) and Part 3 (ISO/TS 12913-3:2019) are technical specifications and offer guidance on how data should be collected and analysed, accordingly <span class="citation" data-cites="ISO12913_2 ISO12913_3">(ISO 2018, 2019)</span> (Part 4, on soundscape design interventions, is currently under development by the working group, also registered as a technical specifications document). Specifically, Part 3 presents the proposed methods for analysing and representing the data collected by the soundscape surveys. Since the development of these standards, the focus has shifted from understanding individual perception to characterising the collective perception of increasingly large groups.</p>
<p>In a recent editorial paper on Soundscape Assessment, Axelsson and colleagues observe that it is important to critically discuss current theories and models in soundscape studies and to examine their effectiveness, while also looking at how to integrate different methods and perspectives for the discipline to make further advancements <span class="citation" data-cites="Axelsson2019editorial">(Axelsson, Guastavino, and Payne 2019)</span>. This work was mainly aimed at addressing the issue of meaningful comparability and representation of soundscape assessments. Part 2 of the ISO 12913 standard itself does not provide ultimate answers: the technical specifications recommend multiple methods, as consensus around a single protocol could not be reached. This diversity of methodological approaches should be interpreted as a fact that soundscape theory is still under development and, for this reason, the standardisation work should probably take a step back and focus on developing a reference method for comparability among soundscape studies, rather than a single protocol for soundscape data collection. Some attempts have indeed already been made in literature for the different methods proposed in the ISO/TS 12913-2:2018 <span class="citation" data-cites="aletta2019exploring">Jo, Seo, and Jeon (2020)</span>. Neither the standard nor the general soundscape literature has settled on effective methods of analysing and representing the data that results from these protocols. Data visualisations are particularly important for understanding and communicating information as multifaceted as soundscape perception <span class="citation" data-cites="tufte2001visual">(Tufte 2001)</span>. Although it is unlikely that any single method will be sufficient, attempts should be made to both facilitate future advancements in this realm and to develop a first step approach that captures the inherent uncertainty in perception studies, since including uncertainty is considered one of the core principles of good data visualisation <span class="citation" data-cites="Midway2020Principles">(Midway 2020)</span>.</p>
<p>This study thus aims to review the consequences of these methods for larger datasets and provide concrete examples for how soundscapes should be represented. In particular, we aim to strengthen the practices for characterising the soundscape of a location, as a collective perception by the users of the location. We also demonstrate how the progress of these tools from their initial scope (measuring and discussing the individual perception of a soundwalk participant) have not kept up with recent advances and requirements for larger-scale soundscape datasets. We question whether there are some issues related to the data collection instruments and data analysis methods as recommended and examine the results of the model framework and mathematical transformations laid out in the ISO technical specifications to guide the interpretation of the soundscape circumplex.</p>
<p>To examine these tools and the questions raised, we apply them to an existing large scale, real-world dataset of soundscape assessments collected according to the ISO methods. Finally, we propose a more holistic and advanced method of representing soundscapes as a probabilistic distribution of perceptions within the circumplex and provide a toolbox for others to use.</p>
</section>
<section id="sec-current" class="level1" data-number="2">
<h1 data-number="2"><span class="header-section-number">2</span> The current ISO 12917 framework</h1>
<p>Although different methods are proposed for data collection in ISO12913 Part 2 <span class="citation" data-cites="ISO12913_2">(ISO 2018)</span>, in the context of this study we focus on the questionnaire-based soundscape assessment (Method A), because it is underpinned by a theoretical relationship among the items of the questionnaire that compose it. The core of this questionnaire is the 8 perceptual attributes (PA) originally derived in <span class="citation" data-cites="Axelsson2010Principal">Axelsson, Nilsson, and Berglund (2010)</span>: pleasant, vibrant (or exciting), eventful, chaotic, annoying, monotonous, uneventful, and calm. In the questionnaire procedure, these PAs are assessed independently of each other, however they are conceptually considered to form a two-dimensional circumplex with <em>{Pleasantness} and </em>Eventfulness* on the x- and y-axis, respectively, where all regions of the space are equally likely to accommodate a given soundscape assessment <span class="citation" data-cites="Aletta2016Soundscape">(Aletta, Kang, and Axelsson 2016)</span>. In <span class="citation" data-cites="Axelsson2010Principal">Axelsson, Nilsson, and Berglund (2010)</span>, a third primary dimension, <em>Familiarity</em> was also found, however this only accounted for 8% of the variance and is typically disregarded as part of the standard circumplex. As will be made clear throughout, the circumplex model has several aspects which make it useful for representing the soundscape perception of a space as a whole.</p>
<section id="coordinate-transformation-into-the-two-primary-dimensions" class="level2" data-number="2.1">
<h2 data-number="2.1" class="anchored" data-anchor-id="coordinate-transformation-into-the-two-primary-dimensions"><span class="header-section-number">2.1</span> Coordinate transformation into the two primary dimensions</h2>
<p>To facilitate the analysis of the PA responses, the Likert scale responses are coded from 1 (Strongly disagree) to 5 (Strongly agree) as ordinal variables. In order to reduce the 8 PA values into a pair of coordinates which can be plotted on the Pleasant-Eventful axes, Part 3 of ISO 12913 <span class="citation" data-cites="ISO12913_3">(ISO 2019)</span> provides a trigonometric transformation, based on the <img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?45%5Cdegree">-relationship between the diagonal axes and the pleasant and eventful axes. This transformation projects the coded values from the individual PAs down onto the primary Pleasantness and Eventfulness dimensions then adds them together to form a single coordinate pair. In theory, this coordinate pair then encapsulates information from all 8 PA dimensions onto a more easily understandable and analysable two dimensions. The ISO coordinates are thus calculated by:</p>
<p><span id="eq-pleasant"><img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?%0A%5Cbegin%7Bsplit%7D%0A%20%20%20%20ISO%20Pleasant%20=%20%5B(pleasant%20-%20annoying)%20+%20%5Ccos%2045%5Cdegree%20*%20(calm%20-%20chaotic)%20%5C%5C%20+%20%5Ccos%2045%5Cdegree%20*%20(vibrant%20-%20monotonous)%5D%20*%201/(4+%5Csqrt%7B32)%7D%0A%5Cend%7Bsplit%7D%0A%5Ctag%7B1%7D"></span></p>
<p><span id="eq-eventful"><img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?%0A%5Cbegin%7Bsplit%7D%0A%20%20%20%20ISO%20Eventful%20=%20%5B(eventful%20-%20uneventful)%20+%20%5Ccos%2045%5Cdegree%20*%20(chaotic%20-%20calm)%20%5C%5C%20+%20%5Ccos%2045%5Cdegree%20*%20(vibrant%20-%20monotonous)%5D%20*%201/(4+%5Csqrt%7B32)%7D%0A%5Cend%7Bsplit%7D%0A%5Ctag%7B2%7D"></span></p>
<p>where the PAs are arranged around the circumplex as shown in Figure&nbsp;1. The <img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?%5Ccos%2045%5Cdegree"> term operates to project the diagonal terms down onto the x and y axes, and the <img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?1%20/%20(4%20+%20%5Csqrt%7B32%7D)"> scales the resulting coordinates to the range (-1, 1). The result of this transformation is demonstrated in Figure&nbsp;1. This treatment of the 8 PAs makes several assumptions and inferences about the relationships between the dimensions. As stated in the standard <span class="citation" data-cites="ISO12913_3">(ISO 2019, 5)</span>:</p>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>According to the two-dimensional model, vibrant soundscapes are both pleasant and eventful, chaotic soundscapes are both eventful and unpleasant, monotonous soundscapes are both unpleasant and uneventful, and finally calm soundscapes are both uneventful and pleasant.</p>
</blockquote>
<div id="fig-radar" class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center anchored">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://drandrewmitchell.com/research/papers/how-to-analyse-jasa/figures/Figure1.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption class="figure-caption">Figure&nbsp;1: Example of representations of two soundscape assessments. Left: Radar plot of two example perceptual attribute (PA) ratings on the Likert scales (1 to 5). Right: Scatter plot of the same assessments on the soundscape circumplex, transformed according to ISO 12913 Part 3.</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
</section>
<section id="summarising-the-soundscape-assessment-of-a-location" class="level2" data-number="2.2">
<h2 data-number="2.2" class="anchored" data-anchor-id="summarising-the-soundscape-assessment-of-a-location"><span class="header-section-number">2.2</span> Summarising the soundscape assessment of a location</h2>
<p>While the assessment methods available are able to record the soundscape perception of a single individual, and that person’s perception is valid for themselves, it is not appropriate to then state that it is representative of the collective perception of that soundscape. In order to characterise the soundscape of a particular space or time, perceptual responses from multiple people must be collected and subsequently summarised or aggregated to describe the general soundscape of the location. The ISO guidelines stipulate a minimum of 20 participants for a soundwalk, with these broken up into sessions of no more than 5 participants at a time. Part 3 then provides the recommended methods for analysing this data.</p>
<p>Annex A.2 of ISO 12913 Part 3 provides the statistical measures to be used on the raw PA responses. The recommended measure of central tendency is the median, while the recommended measure of dispersion is the range. These are chosen as the data is ordinal by nature, however as will be demonstrated later, they have significant limitations. Although it is unclear, the implied intention is then that the median value of each PA is fed into Equation&nbsp;1 and Equation&nbsp;2 presented above to calculate the ISOPleasant and ISOEventful values, which can then be plotted in a two-dimensional scatter plot. Thus the standard suggests that 1) the projection method equations are not applied to individual responses and 2) only the median assessment of a location should be plotted.</p>
</section>
<section id="limitations-of-the-iso" class="level2" data-number="2.3">
<h2 data-number="2.3" class="anchored" data-anchor-id="limitations-of-the-iso"><span class="header-section-number">2.3</span> Limitations of the ISO</h2>
<p>How these methods should be applied to represent the soundscape of a location has not been adequately discussed in previous literature, nor sufficiently in Part 3 of ISO 1293 itself. Indeed, in Section A.3, the technical specifications document state that <span class="citation" data-cites="ISO12913_3">(ISO 2019, 5)</span>:</p>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>Results can be reported in a two-dimensional scatter plot with coordinates for the two dimensions ‘pleasantness’ and ‘eventfulness’. The coordinates for ‘pleasantness’ are plotted on the X-axis, and the coordinates for ‘eventfulness’ on the Y-axis. Every data point in the scatter plot represents one investigated site.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>However, it is not made clear whether this single point on the circumplex can be considered to be a realistic representation of the average perception of the acoustic environment. Effectively, there is no representation of dispersion in the soundscape assessment, nor a recommended use of the range that was calculated as part of the analysis recommend in Section A.2 of Part 3 of the ISO 12913. Absent a suggestion from the ISO 12913 for how the range should be used, we therefore apply this analysis to an existing real-world soundscape dataset to determine whether it provides a useful measure of dispersion. Here we use the data contained in the International Soundscape Database (ISD) <span class="citation" data-cites="Mitchell2021International">(Mitchell, Oberman, Aletta, Erfanian, et al. 2021)</span>, which includes 1,300+ individual responses collected across 13 locations in London and Venice, according to the SSID Protocol, which is based on the ISO methods explored in this paper <span class="citation" data-cites="Mitchell2020Protocol">(Mitchell et al. 2020)</span>.</p>
<p>For any large enough sample for a site, the range will always be from 1 to 5, the maximum and minimum available Likert-scale values. We would expect that collecting more data would result in more information or better precision, however the range will always increase as the sample size increases. As an example, within the ISD data, of the 8 PAs collected at 13 locations (for a total of 104 scales), 88% have a range from 1 to 5 and with larger sample sizes at each location, this percentage would only have increased. Using range to analyse the dispersion provides very limited information for comparing the soundscape assessments of different locations, or of a location under different conditions.</p>
<p>Although the range does not appear to be a useful measure of dispersion, the median does provide a useful measure and appropriately functions to describe the central tendency of the soundscape assessment of the sample. However, by stipulating that the median of each PA should be taken prior to applying the circumplex projection, the ISO procedure only allows for plotting a single scatter point in the circumplex for each location and does not allow for plotting individual responses on the circumplex. This limits the possibilities for visualising the general trends in individual perception across the soundscape. Finally, no example or recommendation for how the circumplex scatter plot should be presented is given in the standard.</p>
<p>The instruments described in the ISO 12913 Part 2 <span class="citation" data-cites="ISO12913_2">(ISO 2018)</span> were originally designed primarily for the context of individual or small group assessments. In these scenarios, the focus is on assessing the particular soundscape perception of the person in question. Recent advances in the soundscape approach since the development of the standards have shifted some focus from individual soundscapes to characterising the overall soundscape of public spaces <span class="citation" data-cites="Mitchell2020Protocol">(Mitchell et al. 2020)</span> and to making comparisons between different groups of people <span class="citation" data-cites="Jeon2018cross">(Jeon et al. 2018)</span>. In this context, a consideration of the natural variation in people’s perception and the variation over time of a soundscape must be a core feature of how the soundscape is discussed. Reducing a public space which may have between tens and tens of thousands of people moving through it in a single day down to the mean (or median, or any other single metric) soundscape assessment often dismisses the reality of the space. Likewise, this overall soundscape of a public space cannot be determined through a ten person soundwalk, as there is no guarantee that the sample of people engaged in the soundwalk is representative of the users of the space (in fact it is likely they would not be).</p>
</section>
</section>
<section id="the-way-forward-pleasant-eventful-coordinates-and-probabilistic-soundscape-representation" class="level1" data-number="3">
<h1 data-number="3"><span class="header-section-number">3</span> The Way Forward: Pleasant-Eventful Coordinates and Probabilistic Soundscape Representation</h1>
<p>Given the identified issues with the recommended methods for statistical analysis and their shortcomings in representing the variation in perception of the soundscape in a space, how then should we discuss or present the results of these soundscape assessments? Ideally, the method will: 1) take advantage of the circumplex coordinates and their ability to be displayed on a scatter plot and treated as continuous variables, 2) scale from a dataset of twenty responses to thousands of responses, 3) facilitate the comparison of the soundscapes of different locations, conditions, and groups, and 4) encapsulate the nuances and diversity of soundscape perception by representing the distribution of responses.</p>
<p>We therefore present a visualisation in Figure&nbsp;2 of the soundscape assessments of several urban spaces included in the ISD <span class="citation" data-cites="Mitchell2021International">(Mitchell, Oberman, Aletta, Erfanian, et al. 2021)</span> which reflects these goals. The specific locations selected from the ISD are chosen for demonstration only and these methods can be applied to any location. Rather than attempting to represent a single individual’s soundscape or of describing a location’s soundscape as a single average assessment (as in <span class="citation" data-cites="Mitchell2021Investigating">Mitchell, Oberman, Aletta, Kachlicka, et al. (2021)</span>), this representation shows the whole range of perception of the users of the space. First, rather than calculating the median response to each PA in the location, then calculating the circumplex coordinates, the coordinates for each individual response are calculated. This results in a vector of ISOPleasant, ISOEventful values which are continuous variables from -1 to +1 and can be analysed statistically by calculating summary statistics (mean, standard deviation, quantiles, etc.) and through the use of regression modelling, which can often be simpler and more familiar than the recommended methods of analysing ordinal data. This also enables each individual’s response to be placed within the pleasant-eventful space. All of the responses for a location can then be plotted, giving an overall scatter plot for a location, as demonstrated in Figure&nbsp;2 (a).</p>
<div>
<details>
<summary>Code</summary>
<div class="sourceCode cell-code" id="cb1" style="background: #f1f3f5;"><pre class="sourceCode python code-with-copy"><code class="sourceCode python"><span id="cb1-1"><span class="im" style="color: #00769E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">import</span> soundscapy <span class="im" style="color: #00769E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">as</span> sspy</span>
<span id="cb1-2"><span class="im" style="color: #00769E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">import</span> matplotlib.pyplot <span class="im" style="color: #00769E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">as</span> plt</span>
<span id="cb1-3"><span class="im" style="color: #00769E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">import</span> pandas <span class="im" style="color: #00769E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">as</span> pd</span>
<span id="cb1-4"></span>
<span id="cb1-5">ssid <span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">=</span> sspy.isd.load()</span>
<span id="cb1-6">ssid <span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">=</span> sspy.isd.remove_lockdown(ssid)</span>
<span id="cb1-7">ssid, excl <span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">=</span> sspy.isd.validate(ssid, allow_paq_na <span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">=</span> <span class="va" style="color: #111111;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">False</span>, verbose<span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">=</span><span class="dv" style="color: #AD0000;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">0</span>)</span>
<span id="cb1-8"></span>
<span id="cb1-9">sspy.plotting.jointplot(</span>
<span id="cb1-10">    sspy.isd.select_location_ids(ssid, <span class="st" style="color: #20794D;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">"PancrasLock"</span>),</span>
<span id="cb1-11">    <span class="co" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;"># title = "(a) Example distribution of the soundscape\nperception of an urban park",</span></span>
<span id="cb1-12">    diagonal_lines <span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">=</span> <span class="va" style="color: #111111;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">True</span>,</span>
<span id="cb1-13">    hue <span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">=</span> <span class="st" style="color: #20794D;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">"LocationID"</span>,</span>
<span id="cb1-14">    legend <span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">=</span> <span class="va" style="color: #111111;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">True</span>,</span>
<span id="cb1-15">    alpha <span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">=</span> <span class="fl" style="color: #AD0000;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">0.75</span>,</span>
<span id="cb1-16">)</span>
<span id="cb1-17">plt.show()</span>
<span id="cb1-18"></span>
<span id="cb1-19">sspy.plotting.density(</span>
<span id="cb1-20">    sspy.isd.select_location_ids(ssid, <span class="st" style="color: #20794D;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">"RegentsParkFields"</span>),</span>
<span id="cb1-21">    <span class="co" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;"># title="(b) Median perception contour and\nscatter plot of individual assessments",</span></span>
<span id="cb1-22">    hue<span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">=</span><span class="st" style="color: #20794D;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">"LocationID"</span>,</span>
<span id="cb1-23">    legend<span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">=</span><span class="va" style="color: #111111;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">True</span>,</span>
<span id="cb1-24">    density_type<span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">=</span><span class="st" style="color: #20794D;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">"simple"</span>,</span>
<span id="cb1-25">    palette<span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">=</span><span class="st" style="color: #20794D;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">"dark:gray"</span>,</span>
<span id="cb1-26">)<span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">;</span></span>
<span id="cb1-27">plt.show()</span>
<span id="cb1-28"></span>
<span id="cb1-29">sspy.plotting.density(</span>
<span id="cb1-30">    sspy.isd.select_location_ids(ssid, [<span class="st" style="color: #20794D;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">'CamdenTown'</span>, <span class="st" style="color: #20794D;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">'RussellSq'</span>, <span class="st" style="color: #20794D;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">'PancrasLock'</span>]),</span>
<span id="cb1-31">    <span class="co" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;"># title="(c) Comparison of the soundscapes\nof three urban spaces",</span></span>
<span id="cb1-32">    hue<span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">=</span><span class="st" style="color: #20794D;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">"LocationID"</span>,</span>
<span id="cb1-33">    alpha<span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">=</span><span class="fl" style="color: #AD0000;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">0.5</span>,</span>
<span id="cb1-34">    palette<span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">=</span><span class="st" style="color: #20794D;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">"husl"</span>,</span>
<span id="cb1-35">    legend<span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">=</span><span class="va" style="color: #111111;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">True</span>,</span>
<span id="cb1-36">    density_type<span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">=</span><span class="st" style="color: #20794D;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">"simple"</span>,</span>
<span id="cb1-37">)<span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">;</span></span>
<span id="cb1-38">plt.show()</span>
<span id="cb1-39"></span>
<span id="cb1-40">ssid[<span class="st" style="color: #20794D;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">"dBLevel"</span>] <span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">=</span> pd.cut(</span>
<span id="cb1-41">    ssid[<span class="st" style="color: #20794D;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">"LAeq_L(A)(dB(SPL))"</span>],</span>
<span id="cb1-42">    bins<span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">=</span>(<span class="dv" style="color: #AD0000;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">0</span>, <span class="dv" style="color: #AD0000;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">63</span>, <span class="dv" style="color: #AD0000;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">150</span>),</span>
<span id="cb1-43">    labels<span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">=</span>(<span class="st" style="color: #20794D;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">"Under 63dB"</span>, <span class="st" style="color: #20794D;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">"Over 63dB"</span>),</span>
<span id="cb1-44">    precision<span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">=</span><span class="dv" style="color: #AD0000;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">1</span>,</span>
<span id="cb1-45">)</span>
<span id="cb1-46"></span>
<span id="cb1-47">sspy.plotting.jointplot(</span>
<span id="cb1-48">    ssid,</span>
<span id="cb1-49">    <span class="co" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;"># title="(d) Soundscape perception as a\nfunction of sound level",</span></span>
<span id="cb1-50">    diagonal_lines<span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">=</span><span class="va" style="color: #111111;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">False</span>,</span>
<span id="cb1-51">    alpha<span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">=</span><span class="fl" style="color: #AD0000;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">0.5</span>,</span>
<span id="cb1-52">    palette<span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">=</span><span class="st" style="color: #20794D;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">"colorblind"</span>,</span>
<span id="cb1-53">    hue<span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">=</span><span class="st" style="color: #20794D;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">"dBLevel"</span>,</span>
<span id="cb1-54">    density_type<span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">=</span><span class="st" style="color: #20794D;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">"simple"</span>,</span>
<span id="cb1-55">    incl_scatter<span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">=</span><span class="va" style="color: #111111;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">False</span>,</span>
<span id="cb1-56">    legend<span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">=</span><span class="va" style="color: #111111;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">True</span>,  <span class="co" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">#</span></span>
<span id="cb1-57">    <span class="co" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;"># ax = axes.flatten()[3]</span></span>
<span id="cb1-58">)<span class="op" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;">;</span></span>
<span id="cb1-59">plt.show()</span>
<span id="cb1-60"></span>
<span id="cb1-61"><span class="co" style="color: #5E5E5E;
background-color: null;
font-style: inherit;"># plt.tight_layout()</span></span></code></pre></div>
</details>
<div id="fig-circ" class="cell quarto-layout-panel" data-execution_count="1">
<figure class="figure">
<div class="quarto-layout-row quarto-layout-valign-top">
<div class="cell-output cell-output-display quarto-layout-cell quarto-layout-cell-subref" style="flex-basis: 47.0%;justify-content: center;">
<div id="fig-circ-1" class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center anchored">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://drandrewmitchell.com/research/papers/how-to-analyse-jasa/index_files/figure-html/fig-circ-output-1.png" class="img-fluid figure-img" data-ref-parent="fig-circ" width="604"></p>
<figcaption class="figure-caption">(a) Example distribution of the soundscape perception of an urban park</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
</div>
<div class="quarto-figure-spacer quarto-layout-cell" style="flex-basis: 3.0%;justify-content: center;">
<p>&nbsp;</p>
</div>
<div class="cell-output cell-output-display quarto-layout-cell quarto-layout-cell-subref" style="flex-basis: 50.0%;justify-content: center;">
<div id="fig-circ-2" class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center anchored">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://drandrewmitchell.com/research/papers/how-to-analyse-jasa/index_files/figure-html/fig-circ-output-2.png" class="img-fluid figure-img" data-ref-parent="fig-circ" width="470"></p>
<figcaption class="figure-caption">(b) Median perception contour and scatter plot of individual assessments</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
</div>
</div>
<div class="quarto-layout-row quarto-layout-valign-top">
<div class="cell-output cell-output-display quarto-layout-cell quarto-layout-cell-subref" style="flex-basis: 50.0%;justify-content: center;">
<div id="fig-circ-3" class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center anchored">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://drandrewmitchell.com/research/papers/how-to-analyse-jasa/index_files/figure-html/fig-circ-output-3.png" class="img-fluid figure-img" data-ref-parent="fig-circ" width="470"></p>
<figcaption class="figure-caption">(c) Comparison of the soundscapes of three urban spaces</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
</div>
<div class="quarto-figure-spacer quarto-layout-cell" style="flex-basis: 3.0%;justify-content: center;">
<p>&nbsp;</p>
</div>
<div class="cell-output cell-output-display quarto-layout-cell quarto-layout-cell-subref" style="flex-basis: 47.0%;justify-content: center;">
<div id="fig-circ-4" class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center anchored">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://drandrewmitchell.com/research/papers/how-to-analyse-jasa/index_files/figure-html/fig-circ-output-4.png" class="img-fluid figure-img" data-ref-parent="fig-circ" width="604"></p>
<figcaption class="figure-caption">(d) Soundscape perception as a function of sound level</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
</div>
</div>
<p></p><figcaption class="figure-caption">Figure&nbsp;2: A demonstration of some use cases of representing soundscape perception as probabilistic distributions. Data is drawn from the International Soundscape Database (ISD) and is used for demonstration only. (a) Demonstrates a high level of detail for presenting the bivariate distribution of soundscape perception in a park (Russell Square in London). (b) Simplified view of the distribution using the 50th percentile contour. The assessments impacted by a series of helicopter fly-overs are made obvious in the chaotic quadrant. (c) A comparison of three popular public spaces in London. Their overlapping regions can reveal when and how their soundscapes may be similar. (d) A comparison across the full ISD for soundscape perception at <img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?%3C65%20dB%20L_%7BAeq%7D"> and <img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?%3E%2065%20dBA">. The introduction of other acoustic, environmental, and contextual data can reveal new and complex relationships with the soundscape perception.</figcaption><p></p>
</figure>
</div>
</div>
<p>Once these individual responses are plotted, we then overlay a heatmap of the bivariate distribution (with isodensity curves for each decile) and marginal distribution plots<sup>1</sup>. In this way, three primary characteristics of the soundscape perception can be seen:</p>
<ol type="1">
<li><p>The distribution across both pleasantness and eventfulness, including the central tendency, the dispersion, and any skewness in the response;</p></li>
<li><p>The general shape of the soundscape within the space - in this case, Russell Sq is almost entirely in the pleasant half but is split relatively evenly across the eventfulness space, meaning while it is perceived as generally pleasant, it is not strongly calm or vibrant;</p></li>
<li><p>The degree of agreement about the soundscape perception among the sample - there appears to be a relatively high agreement about the character of Russell Sq, as demonstrated by the compactness of the distribution, but this is not the case for every location.</p></li>
</ol>
<p>Figure&nbsp;2 (a) includes several in-depth visualisations of the distribution of soundscape assessments, however the detail included can make further analysis difficult. In particular, a decile heatmap is so visually busy that, in our experience, it is not possible to plot more than one soundscape distribution at a time without the figure becoming overly busy. It also can make it difficult to truly grasp point 2, the general shape of the soundscape. To facilitate this, the soundscape can be represented by its 50th percentile contour, as demonstrated in Figure&nbsp;2 (b) where the shaded portion contains 50% of the responses. This simplified view of the distribution presents several advantages, as is demonstrated in Figure&nbsp;2 (c) and Figure&nbsp;2 (d) and takes inspiration from the recommendation in the ISO standard to use the median as a summary statistic. In our testing, the 50th percentile contour has proved useful, clear, and compact, however this should not be taken as the definitive correct percentile cutoff. Further work will need to be done to validate the precise presentation.</p>
<p>When visualised this way, it is possible to identify outliers and responses which are the result of anomalous sound events. For instance if during a survey session at a calm park, a fleet of helicopters flies overhead, driving the participants to respond that the soundscape is highly chaotic, we would see a group of scatter points in the chaotic quadrant which appear obviously outside the general pattern of responses. Often, these responses would be entirely discarded as outliers or the surveys and soundwalks would be halted entirely – ignoring what is in fact a significant impact on that location, its soundscape, and how useful it may be for the community. Alternatively, they would be naively included within the statistical analysis, significantly impacting the central tendency and dispersion metrics (i.e.&nbsp;median and range) without consideration for the context. This is the situation shown in Figure&nbsp;2 (b) where it is obvious that there is strong agreement that Regents Park Fields is highly pleasant and calm, however we can see numerous responses which assessed it as highly chaotic. These responses were taken when a series of military helicopter flyovers drastically changed the sound environment of the space for several minutes.</p>
<p>Figure&nbsp;2 (c) demonstrates how this simplified 50th percentile contour representation makes it possible to compare the soundscape of several locations in a sophisticated way. The soundscape assessments of three urban spaces, Camden Town, Pancras Lock, and Russell Square, are shown overlaid with each other. We can see that Camden Town, a busy and crowded street corner with high levels of traffic noise and amplified music, is generally perceived as chaotic, but the median contour shape which characterises it also crosses over into the vibrant quadrant. We can also see that, for a part of the sample, Russell Square and Pancras Lock are both perceived as similarly pleasant, however some portion of the responses perceived Pancras Lock as being somewhat chaotic and annoying. This kind of visualisation can highlight these similarities between the soundscapes in the locations and identify how they differ. From here, further investigation could lead us to answer what factors led to those people perceiving the location as unpleasant, and what similarities the soundscape of Pancras Lock has with Russell Square that could perhaps be enhanced to increase the proportion of people perceiving it as more pleasant.</p>
<p>In addition to solely analysing the distributions of the perceptual responses themselves, this method can also be combined with other acoustic, environmental, and contextual data. The final example, in Figure&nbsp;2 (d) demonstrates how this method can better demonstrate the complex relationships between acoustic features of the sound environment and the soundscape perception. The data in the ISD includes ~30-s-long binaural audio recordings taken while each participant was responding to the soundscape survey, providing an indication of the exact sound environment they were exposed to. For Figure&nbsp;2 (d) the entire dataset of 1,338 responses at all 13 locations has been split according to the analysis of these recordings giving a set of less than 65 dB <img src="https://latex.codecogs.com/png.latex?L_%7BAeq%7D"> and a set of more than 65 dB. The bivariate distributions of these two conditions are then plotted.</p>
<p>By presenting soundscape perception as a bivariate distributional shape on the circumplex, practitioners are obligated to address two key aspects of perception that are too often ignored: the distribution of potential responses and the eventful dimension. The array of potential responses to an environment is a crucial factor in assessing the successful design of a space and represents the reality of perception. There is no single perceptual outcome of an environment; it will always include some randomness inherent in human perception and this should be reflected in how we present soundscape assessments. Similarly, the eventful dimension is crucial to understanding how an environment is perceived and can have important impacts on the health and well-being of the users. Recent evidence also suggests that there is a more direct relationship between acoustic characteristics and the perception of eventfulness, while pleasantness is more dependent on context <span class="citation" data-cites="Mitchell2021Investigating">(Mitchell, Oberman, Aletta, Kachlicka, et al. 2021)</span>. Studies that explore the correlations between acoustic features and annoyance (or pleasantness) without considering eventfulness are perhaps missing the most direct effect of the acoustic features.</p>
</section>
<section id="making-use-of-the-soundscape-circumplex" class="level1" data-number="4">
<h1 data-number="4"><span class="header-section-number">4</span> Making Use of the Soundscape Circumplex</h1>
<p>There are various potential methods for integrating the probabilistic soundscape approach into a design and intervention setting. Representing the soundscape as a shape within the circumplex provides flexibility in setting design goals for a space. Not all spaces can or should have the same soundscape and soundscapes should be treated as dynamic, not static; identifying and creating an appropriate soundscape for the particular use case of a space is crucial to guiding its design. Proper forward-looking design of a soundscape would involve defining the desired shape and distribution of perceptions in the space. This can be achieved by drawing the desired shape in the circumplex and testing interventions which will bring the existing soundscape closer to the desired perception. A soundscape may need to be perceived as vibrant during the day and calm for some portion of the evening, meaning the desired shape should primarily sit within the vibrant quadrant but have some overlap into calm. This also enables designers to recognise the limitations of their environment and acknowledge that it is not always possible to transform a highly chaotic soundscape into a calm one. In these cases, instead the focus should be placed on shifting the distribution to some degree in a positive direction. The most sophisticated method of setting design goals is therefore to identify the desired shape which represents the variety of desired outcomes, and focus on designs and interventions which are most successful in matching the predicted outcome with that goal.</p>
<p>Although the visualisations shown in Figure&nbsp;2 are a powerful tool for viewing, analysing, and discussing the multi-dimensional aspects of soundscape perception, there are certainly cases where simpler metrics are needed to aid discussion and to set design goals. For this, the underlying process of calculating the ISOPleasant and ISOEventful coordinates for each individual response is still the first step in analysing the quantitative soundscape data. These sets of coordinates can then be analysed and summarised in various ways. One approach which takes inspiration from noise annoyance <span class="citation" data-cites="ISO15666">(ISO/TS 15666:2021 2021)</span>, is to discuss the “percent of people likely to perceive” a soundscape as pleasant, vibrant, etc. when it is necessary to use numerical descriptions. In this way, a numerical design goal could also be set as e.g.&nbsp;‘the soundscape should be likely to be perceived as pleasant by at least 75% of users’ or the result of an intervention presented as e.g.&nbsp;‘the likelihood of the soundscape being perceived as calm increased from 30% to 55%’. These numbers can be drawn from either actual surveys or from the results of predictive models.</p>
<p>Although acknowledging the distribution of responses is crucial, it is sometimes necessary to summarise locations down to a single point to compare many different locations and to easily investigate how the soundscape assessment has generally changed over time. For this purpose, the mean of the ISOPleasant and ISOEventful values across all respondents is calculated to result in a single coordinate point per location. This clearly mirrors the original intent of the coordinate transformation presented in the ISO, but by applying the transformation first to each individual assessment then calculating the mean value, it maintains a direct link to the distributions shown in Figure&nbsp;2. An example plot using the mean response of each location to compare many locations and to demonstrate change in soundscape perception can be found in Figure 5 of <span class="citation" data-cites="Mitchell2021Investigating">Mitchell, Oberman, Aletta, Kachlicka, et al. (2021)</span>. The key to all of these analysis methods, whether they be the distributional plots shown in Figure&nbsp;2, the numerical summaries, or the use of other standard statistical analyses is treating the soundscape of the space or group as a collective perception as expressed by a vector of individual circumplex coordinates.</p>
<p>Finally, the primary concern addressed by this method is the analysis of larger soundscape datasets, compared to what is suggested in the standard. This is necessary in order to statistically describe the groups or sub-groups being investigated, and is typically taken to need a minimum of ~30 responses per group (although the full dataset, made up of many groups and locations may have many more responses in total, as in the ISD) <span class="citation" data-cites="Hong2015Influence PuyanaRomero2016Modelling">(e.g. Hong and Jeon 2015; Puyana Romero et al. 2016)</span>. It is unlikely that the bivariate distributions plots shown are appropriate for small datasets. However, the process of calculating the ISO coordinates for each individual response and treating this as a set of continuous values to subject to other statistical analysis holds for all sample sizes. Pleasant-eventful scatterplots are still useful for comparing differences in individual responses and appropriate methods of summarising small sample data should be explored (such as the univariate scatterplots described in <span class="citation" data-cites="Weissgerber2015Bar">Weissgerber et al. (2015)</span>).</p>
<section id="limitations-of-the-circumplex-and-quantitative-analysis" class="level2" data-number="4.1">
<h2 data-number="4.1" class="anchored" data-anchor-id="limitations-of-the-circumplex-and-quantitative-analysis"><span class="header-section-number">4.1</span> Limitations of the circumplex and quantitative analysis</h2>
<p>The method presented here is a solution for representing the soundscape of a space, which requires considering the perception of many people, but it is important to note that this is only one (very important) goal of the soundscape approach. Psychological and sociological investigations of people’s relationship to their sound environment and the interactions between social contexts and individual perception are a crucial aspect of the field for which this approach would likely not be sufficient <span class="citation" data-cites="Bild2018Public">(Bild et al. 2018)</span>. Open-response questions, structured interviews, and mixed-methods studies can provide additional insight into how people experience their environment and should be considered alongside or preceding this focus on how a space is likely to be perceived on a larger scale.</p>
<p>These other approaches are not in opposition to the methods proposed here, but instead further expand our view. The circumplex is a limited view of soundscape perception (this is made obvious by the fact that it excludes the third component, <em>familiarity</em>, identified in <span class="citation" data-cites="Axelsson2010Principal">Axelsson, Nilsson, and Berglund (2010)</span>) but it is an exceptionally rich tool for dealing with the two primary aspects of soundscape perception which can readily expand the much more limited view provided by existing noise and annoyance assessment tools. Aspects of the psychological and sociological emphasis can also be integrated into a circumplex-focused approach, as demonstrated in <span class="citation" data-cites="Erfanian2021Psychological">Erfanian et al. (2021)</span>, where personal factors such as age, gender, and psychological well-being were analysed in terms of how they mediated the ISOPleasant and ISOEventful outcomes.</p>
<p>There has been some discussion regarding the interdependence of the PAs and the strict validity of the 90and 45 relationships between the attributes <span class="citation" data-cites="Lionello2021Introducing">(Lionello et al. 2021)</span>. Further work has indicated that the scaling between the attributes may vary, but the underlying relationships hold. It is for this reason that we have taken the coordinate projection as the starting point of this critique. It should also be noted that the particular PA descriptors used in ISO 12913 are intended for outdoor environments and should not be directly applied to indoor spaces. However, a proposed set of descriptors for some indoor environments has been derived which further confirms the validity of the circumplex relationships <span class="citation" data-cites="Torresin2020Indoor">(Torresin et al. 2020)</span>. The methods proposed here should be directly applicable to indoor spaces by using the comfort/content descriptors as well as to any other translations of soundscape descriptors into other languages <span class="citation" data-cites="Aletta2020Soundscape">(Aletta et al. 2020)</span> as long as the dimensional relationships of the circumplex are maintained.</p>
</section>
</section>
<section id="conclusions" class="level1" data-number="5">
<h1 data-number="5"><span class="header-section-number">5</span> Conclusions</h1>
<p>Soundscape studies have been steadily growing as a research field over the past three decades. Their relevance for the planning and design of urban spaces is now generally acknowledged by both the academic and practitioners’ communities. Yet, for their contribution in shaping better environments to be meaningful, it is necessary to agree on common methodological approaches and techniques to analyse and present standardised soundscape data. Therefore, the general goal of this work is to consider some of the questions that may still have been left unanswered by the ISO 12913 series when it comes to optimal ways to analyse and represent soundscape data coming from the ISO standardised protocols. As a result, we propose a method for presenting the results of standardised assessments as a distribution of soundscape perception within the circumplex space. This method provides an opportunity to conduct a nuanced discussion of soundscape perception which considers the variety of individual responses. The tools for generating these circumplex visualisations are made openly available as well. This shift is part of a move towards a more holistic approach to urban noise and to integrating the soundscape approach into urban design and regulations.</p>
</section>
<section id="data-and-code-availability" class="level1" data-number="6">
<h1 data-number="6"><span class="header-section-number">6</span> Data and Code Availability</h1>
<p>The data used in this study are openly available as v0.2.3 of the International Soundscape Database (ISD) at <a href="https://zenodo.org/record/5578572">https://zenodo.org/record/5578572</a>. A library of python functions for producing the type of plots presented (using the seaborn plotting library <span class="citation" data-cites="Waskom2021">(Waskom 2021)</span>) and an interactive Jupyter notebook which provides a tutorial for using this code, working with the ISD data, and recreating the figures of this paper has been made available as part of the ISD.</p>
</section>
<section id="acknowledgements" class="level1" data-number="7">
<h1 data-number="7"><span class="header-section-number">7</span> Acknowledgements</h1>
<p>This project has received funding from the European Research Council (ERC) under the European Union’s Horizon 2020 research and innovation program (grant agreement No.&nbsp;740696, project title: Soundscape Indices - SSID). We would like to acknowledge Matteo Lionello for the helpful discussions, and (in alphabetical order) Mercede Erfanian, Magdalena Kachlicka, and Tin Oberman for the helpful discussions and the data collection support.</p>



</section>


<div id="quarto-appendix" class="default"><section class="quarto-appendix-contents"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">References</h2><div id="refs" class="references csl-bib-body hanging-indent">
<div id="ref-aletta2019exploring" class="csl-entry">
Aletta, Francesco, Claudia Guattari, Luca Evangelisti, Francesco Asdrubali, Tin Oberman, and Jian Kang. 2019. <span>“Exploring the Compatibility of <span>‘Method a’</span> and <span>‘Method b’</span> Data Collection Protocols Reported in the ISO/TS 12913-2: 2018 for Urban Soundscape via a Soundwalk.”</span> <em>Applied Acoustics</em> 155: 190–203.
</div>
<div id="ref-Aletta2016Soundscape" class="csl-entry">
Aletta, Francesco, Jian Kang, and Östen Axelsson. 2016. <span>“<span class="nocase">Soundscape descriptors and a conceptual framework for developing predictive soundscape models</span>.”</span> <em>Landscape and Urban Planning</em> 149 (July): 65–74. <a href="https://doi.org/10.1016/j.landurbplan.2016.02.001">https://doi.org/10.1016/j.landurbplan.2016.02.001</a>.
</div>
<div id="ref-Aletta2020Soundscape" class="csl-entry">
Aletta, Francesco, Tin Oberman, Östen Axelsson, Hui Xie, Yuan Zhang, Siu-Kit Lau, Shiu-Keung Tang, et al. 2020. <span>“Soundscape Assessment: Towards a Validated Translation of Perceptual Attributes in Different Languages.”</span> In <em>INTER-NOISE and NOISE-CON Congress and Conference Proceedings</em>, 261:3137–46. 3. Institute of Noise Control Engineering.
</div>
<div id="ref-Axelsson2019editorial" class="csl-entry">
Axelsson, Östen, Catherine Guastavino, and Sarah R. Payne. 2019. <span>“Editorial: Soundscape Assessment.”</span> <em>Frontiers in Psychology</em> 10: 2514. <a href="https://doi.org/10.3389/fpsyg.2019.02514">https://doi.org/10.3389/fpsyg.2019.02514</a>.
</div>
<div id="ref-Axelsson2010Principal" class="csl-entry">
Axelsson, Östen, Mats E. Nilsson, and Birgitta Berglund. 2010. <span>“<span class="nocase">A principal components model of soundscape perception</span>.”</span> <em>The Journal of the Acoustical Society of America</em> 128 (5): 2836–46. <a href="https://doi.org/10.1121/1.3493436">https://doi.org/10.1121/1.3493436</a>.
</div>
<div id="ref-Bild2018Public" class="csl-entry">
Bild, Edda, Karin Pfeffer, Matt Coler, Ori Rubin, and Luca Bertolini. 2018. <span>“<span class="nocase">Public Space Users’ Soundscape Evaluations in Relation to Their Activities. An Amsterdam-Based Study</span>.”</span> <em>Frontiers in Psychology</em> 9: 1593. <a href="https://doi.org/10.3389/fpsyg.2018.01593">https://doi.org/10.3389/fpsyg.2018.01593</a>.
</div>
<div id="ref-Erfanian2021Psychological" class="csl-entry">
Erfanian, Mercede, Andrew Mitchell, Francesco Aletta, and Jian Kang. 2021. <span>“Psychological Well-Being and Demographic Factors Can Mediate Soundscape Pleasantness and Eventfulness: A Large Sample Study.”</span> <em>Journal of Environmental Psychology</em> 77 (October): 101660. <a href="https://doi.org/10.1016/j.jenvp.2021.101660">https://doi.org/10.1016/j.jenvp.2021.101660</a>.
</div>
<div id="ref-Hong2015Influence" class="csl-entry">
Hong, Joo Young, and Jin Yong Jeon. 2015. <span>“Influence of Urban Contexts on Soundscape Perceptions: A Structural Equation Modeling Approach.”</span> <em>Landscape and Urban Planning</em> 141 (September): 78–87. <a href="https://doi.org/10.1016/j.landurbplan.2015.05.004">https://doi.org/10.1016/j.landurbplan.2015.05.004</a>.
</div>
<div id="ref-ISO12913_1" class="csl-entry">
ISO. 2014. <span>“<span class="nocase">ISO 12913-1:2014 Acoustics - Soundscape - Part 1: Definition and conceptual framework</span>.”</span> Geneva: <span>International Organisation for Standardisation</span>; ISO Geneva.
</div>
<div id="ref-ISO12913_2" class="csl-entry">
———. 2018. <span>“<span class="nocase">ISO/TS 12913-2:2018 Acoustics - Soundscape - Part 2: Data collection and reporting requirements</span>.”</span> Geneva: <span>International Organisation for Standardisation</span>; ISO Geneva.
</div>
<div id="ref-ISO12913_3" class="csl-entry">
———. 2019. <span>“<span class="nocase">ISO/TS 12913-3:2019 Acoustics - Soundscape - Part 3: Data analysis</span>.”</span> <span>International Organisation for Standardisation</span>. <a href="https://bsol.bsigroup.com/Bibliographic/BibliographicInfoData/000000000030386393">https://bsol.bsigroup.com/Bibliographic/BibliographicInfoData/000000000030386393</a>.
</div>
<div id="ref-ISO15666" class="csl-entry">
ISO/TS 15666:2021. 2021. <span>“<span>Acoustics</span> – Assessment of Noise Annoyance by Means of Social and Socio-Acoustic Surveys.”</span>
</div>
<div id="ref-Jeon2018cross" class="csl-entry">
Jeon, Jin Yong, Joo Young Hong, Catherine Lavandier, Jeanne Lafon, Östen Axelsson, and Malin Hurtig. 2018. <span>“<span class="nocase">A cross-national comparison in assessment of urban park soundscapes in France, Korea, and Sweden through laboratory experiments</span>.”</span> <em>Applied Acoustics</em>. <a href="https://doi.org/10.1016/j.apacoust.2017.12.016">https://doi.org/10.1016/j.apacoust.2017.12.016</a>.
</div>
<div id="ref-jo2020soundscape" class="csl-entry">
Jo, Hyun In, Rosa Seo, and Jin Yong Jeon. 2020. <span>“Soundscape Assessment Methods: Compatibility of Questionnaires and Narrative Interview Based on ISO 12913-2.”</span> In <em>INTER-NOISE and NOISE-CON Congress and Conference Proceedings</em>, 261:3509–18. 3. Institute of Noise Control Engineering.
</div>
<div id="ref-kang2016ten" class="csl-entry">
Kang, Jian, Francesco Aletta, Truls T Gjestland, Lex A Brown, Dick Botteldooren, Brigitte Schulte-Fortkamp, Peter Lercher, et al. 2016. <span>“Ten Questions on the Soundscapes of the Built Environment.”</span> <em>Building and Environment</em> 108: 284–94.
</div>
<div id="ref-Lionello2021Introducing" class="csl-entry">
Lionello, Matteo, Francesco Aletta, Andrew Mitchell, and Jian Kang. 2021. <span>“Introducing a Method for Intervals Correction on Multiple Likert Scales: A Case Study on an Urban Soundscape Data Collection Instrument.”</span> <em>Frontiers in Psychology</em> 11: 3943. <a href="https://doi.org/10.3389/fpsyg.2020.602831">https://doi.org/10.3389/fpsyg.2020.602831</a>.
</div>
<div id="ref-Midway2020Principles" class="csl-entry">
Midway, Stephen R. 2020. <span>“Principles of Effective Data Visualization.”</span> <em>Patterns</em> 1 (9): 100141. https://doi.org/<a href="https://doi.org/10.1016/j.patter.2020.100141">https://doi.org/10.1016/j.patter.2020.100141</a>.
</div>
<div id="ref-Mitchell2020Protocol" class="csl-entry">
Mitchell, Andrew, Tin Oberman, Francesco Aletta, Mercede Erfanian, Magdalena Kachlicka, Matteo Lionello, and Jian Kang. 2020. <span>“<span class="nocase">The Soundscape Indices (SSID) Protocol: A Method for Urban Soundscape Surveys—Questionnaires with Acoustical and Contextual Information</span>.”</span> <em>Applied Sciences</em> 10 (7): 2397. <a href="https://doi.org/10.3390/app10072397">https://doi.org/10.3390/app10072397</a>.
</div>
<div id="ref-Mitchell2021International" class="csl-entry">
———. 2021. <span>“<span class="nocase">The International Soundscape Database: An integrated multimedia database of urban soundscape surveys – questionnaires with acoustical and contextual information</span>.”</span> Zenodo. <a href="https://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.5578572">https://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.5578572</a>.
</div>
<div id="ref-Mitchell2021Investigating" class="csl-entry">
Mitchell, Andrew, Tin Oberman, Francesco Aletta, Magdalena Kachlicka, Matteo Lionello, Mercede Erfanian, and Jian Kang. 2021. <span>“Investigating Urban Soundscapes of the <span>COVID</span>-19 Lockdown: A Predictive Soundscape Modeling Approach.”</span> <em>The Journal of the Acoustical Society of America</em> 150 (6): 4474–88. <a href="https://doi.org/10.1121/10.0008928">https://doi.org/10.1121/10.0008928</a>.
</div>
<div id="ref-PuyanaRomero2016Modelling" class="csl-entry">
Puyana Romero, Virginia, Luigi Maffei, Giovanni Brambilla, and Giuseppe Ciaburro. 2016. <span>“Modelling the Soundscape Quality of Urban Waterfronts by Artificial Neural Networks.”</span> <em>Applied Acoustics</em> 111 (October): 121–28. <a href="https://doi.org/10.1016/j.apacoust.2016.04.019">https://doi.org/10.1016/j.apacoust.2016.04.019</a>.
</div>
<div id="ref-SoundscapeOursonicSchafer" class="csl-entry">
Schafer, R. Murray. 1977. <em><span class="nocase">The Soundscape: Our sonic environment and the tuning of the world</span></em>.
</div>
<div id="ref-silverman2018density" class="csl-entry">
Silverman, Bernard W. 2018. <em>Density Estimation for Statistics and Data Analysis</em>. Routledge.
</div>
<div id="ref-Southworth1969sonic" class="csl-entry">
Southworth, Michael. 1969. <span>“<span class="nocase">The sonic environment of cities</span>.”</span> <em>Environment and Behavior</em>. <a href="https://doi.org/10.1177/001391656900100104">https://doi.org/10.1177/001391656900100104</a>.
</div>
<div id="ref-Torresin2020Indoor" class="csl-entry">
Torresin, Simone, Rossano Albatici, Francesco Aletta, Francesco Babich, Tin Oberman, Stefano Siboni, and Jian Kang. 2020. <span>“<span class="nocase">Indoor soundscape assessment: A principal components model of acoustic perception in residential buildings</span>.”</span> <em>Building and Environment</em> 182 (September): 107152. <a href="https://doi.org/10.1016/j.buildenv.2020.107152">https://doi.org/10.1016/j.buildenv.2020.107152</a>.
</div>
<div id="ref-tufte2001visual" class="csl-entry">
Tufte, Edward. 2001. <span>“The Visual Display of Quantitative Information.”</span> Cheshire: Graphic Press.–2001.–213 p.
</div>
<div id="ref-Waskom2021" class="csl-entry">
Waskom, Michael L. 2021. <span>“Seaborn: Statistical Data Visualization.”</span> <em>Journal of Open Source Software</em> 6 (60): 3021. <a href="https://doi.org/10.21105/joss.03021">https://doi.org/10.21105/joss.03021</a>.
</div>
<div id="ref-Weissgerber2015Bar" class="csl-entry">
Weissgerber, Tracey L., Natasa M. Milic, Stacey J. Winham, and Vesna D. Garovic. 2015. <span>“Beyond Bar and Line Graphs: Time for a New Data Presentation Paradigm.”</span> <em>PLOS Biology</em> 13 (4): 1–10. <a href="https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pbio.1002128">https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pbio.1002128</a>.
</div>
<div id="ref-westerkamp2002linking" class="csl-entry">
Westerkamp, Hildegard. 2002. <span>“Linking Soundscape Composition and Acoustic Ecology.”</span> <em>Organised Sound</em> 7 (1): 51–56.
</div>
</div></section><section id="footnotes" class="footnotes footnotes-end-of-document"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">Footnotes</h2>

<ol>
<li id="fn1"><p>The specifics of the bivariate kernel density estimation <span class="citation" data-cites="silverman2018density">(Silverman 2018)</span> are beyond the scope of this discussion and the most appropriate hyperparameters (e.g.&nbsp;estimation methods, smoothing factors) for this visualisation may need to be further explored. These parameters will likely depend on the specific dataset used.↩︎</p></li>
</ol>
</section><section class="quarto-appendix-contents"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">Reuse</h2><div id="quarto-reuse" class="quarto-appendix-contents"><div><a rel="license" href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</a></div></div></section><section class="quarto-appendix-contents"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">Citation</h2><div><div class="quarto-appendix-secondary-label">BibTeX citation:</div><pre class="sourceCode code-with-copy quarto-appendix-bibtex"><code class="sourceCode bibtex">@article{mitchell2022,
  author = {Mitchell, Andrew and Aletta, Francesco and Kang, Jian},
  title = {How to Analyse and Represent Quantitative Soundscape Data},
  journal = {JASA Express Letters},
  volume = {2},
  number = {3},
  pages = {037201},
  date = {2022-03-16},
  url = {https://pubs.aip.org/asa/jel/article/2/3/037201/2845750},
  doi = {10.1121/10.0009794},
  langid = {en},
  abstract = {This study first examines the methods presented in ISO
    12913 for analysing and representing soundscape data by applying
    them to a large existing database of soundscape assessments. The key
    issue identified is the inability of the standard methods to
    summarise the soundscape of locations and groups. The presented
    solution inherently considers the variety of responses within a
    group and provides an open-source visualisation tool to facilitate a
    nuanced approach to soundscape assessment and design. Several
    demonstrations of the soundscape distribution of urban spaces are
    presented, along with proposals for how this approach can be used
    and developed.}
}
</code></pre><div class="quarto-appendix-secondary-label">For attribution, please cite this work as:</div><div id="ref-mitchell2022" class="csl-entry quarto-appendix-citeas">
Mitchell, Andrew, Francesco Aletta, and Jian Kang. 2022. <span>“How to
Analyse and Represent Quantitative Soundscape Data.”</span> <em>JASA
Express Letters</em> 2 (March): 037201. <a href="https://doi.org/10.1121/10.0009794">https://doi.org/10.1121/10.0009794</a>.
</div></div></section></div> ]]></description>
  <category>journal-articles</category>
  <guid>https://drandrewmitchell.com/research/papers/how-to-analyse-jasa/index.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Wed, 16 Mar 2022 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
</item>
</channel>
</rss>
